<chapter id="svn.serverconfig">
  <title>Server Configuration</title>

  <para>A Subversion repository can be accessed simultaneously by
    clients running on the same machine on which the repository
    resides using the <literal>file://</literal> method.  But the
    typical Subversion setup involves a single server machine being
    accessed from clients on computers all over the office&mdash;or,
    perhaps, all over the world.</para>

  <para>This chapter describes how to get your Subversion repository
    exposed outside its host machine for use by remote clients.  We
    will cover Subversion's currently available server mechanisms,
    discussing the configuration and use of each.  After reading this
    chapter, you should be able to decide which networking setup is
    right for your needs, as well as understand how to enable such a
    setup on your host computer.</para>


  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.serverconfig.overview">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>Subversion was designed with an abstract network layer.
      This means that a repository can be programmatically accessed by
      any sort of server process, and the client <quote>repository
      access</quote> API allows programmers to write plug-ins that
      speak relevant network protocols.  In theory, Subversion can use
      an infinite number of network implementations.  In practice,
      there are only two servers at the time of this writing.</para>

    <para>Apache is an extremely popular web server; using the
      <command>mod_dav_svn</command> module, Apache can access a
      repository and make it available to clients via the
      WebDAV/DeltaV protocol, which is an extension of HTTP.  Because
      Apache is an extremely extensible server, it provides a number
      of features <quote>for free,</quote> such as encrypted SSL
      communication, logging, integration with a number of third-party
      authentication systems, and limited built-in web browsing of
      repositories.</para>

    <para>In the other corner is <command>svnserve</command>: a small,
      lightweight server program that speaks a custom protocol with
      clients.  Because its protocol is explicitly designed for
      Subversion and is stateful (unlike HTTP), it provides
      significantly faster network operations&mdash;but at the cost of
      some features as well.  While it can use SASL to provide a
      variety of authentication and encryption options, it has no
      logging or built-in web browsing.  It is, however, extremely
      easy to set up and is often the best option for small teams just
      starting out with Subversion.</para>

    <para>A third option is to use <command>svnserve</command>
      tunneled over an SSH connection.  Even though this scenario
      still uses <command>svnserve</command>, it differs quite a bit
      in features from a traditional <command>svnserve</command>
      deployment.  SSH is used to encrypt all communication.  SSH is
      also used exclusively to authenticate, so real system accounts
      are required on the server host (unlike
      vanilla <command>svnserve</command>, which has its own private
      user accounts).  Finally, because this setup requires that each
      user spawn a private, temporary <command>svnserve</command>
      process, it's equivalent (from a permissions point of view) to
      allowing a group of local users to all access the repository
      via <literal>file://</literal> URLs. Path-based access control
      has no meaning, since each user is accessing the repository
      database files directly.</para>

    <para><xref linkend="svn.serverconfig.overview.tbl-1"/> provides a
      quick summary of the three typical server deployments.</para>

    <table id="svn.serverconfig.overview.tbl-1">
      <title>Comparison of subversion server options</title>
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Feature</entry>
            <entry>Apache + mod_dav_svn</entry>
            <entry>svnserve</entry>
            <entry>svnserve over SSH</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Authentication options</entry>
            <entry>HTTP(S) basic auth, X.509 certificates, LDAP, NTLM, or
              any other mechanism available to Apache httpd</entry>
            <entry>CRAM-MD5 by default;  LDAP, NTLM, or any other mechanism
              available to SASL</entry>
            <entry>SSH</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>User account options</entry>
            <entry>Private 'users' file, or other mechanisms
            available to Apache httpd (LDAP, SQL, etc.)</entry>
            <entry>Private 'users' file, or other mechanisms available
              to SASL (LDAP, SQL, etc.)</entry>
            <entry>System accounts</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Authorization options</entry>
            <entry>Read/write access can be granted over the whole
              repository, or specified per path</entry>
            <entry>Read/write access can be granted over the whole
              repository, or specified per path</entry>
            <entry>Read/write access only grantable over the whole
              repository</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Encryption</entry>
            <entry>Available via optional SSL</entry>
            <entry>Available via optional SASL features</entry>
            <entry>Inherent in SSH connection</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Logging</entry>
            <entry>Full Apache logs of each HTTP request, with
            optional <quote>high-level</quote> logging of general
            client operations</entry>
            <entry>No logging</entry>
            <entry>No logging</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Interoperability</entry>
            <entry>Accessible by other WebDAV clients</entry>
            <entry>Talks only to svn clients</entry>
            <entry>Talks only to svn clients</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Web viewing</entry>
            <entry>Limited built-in support, or via third-party tools
              such as ViewVC</entry>
            <entry>Only via third-party tools such as ViewVC</entry>
            <entry>Only via third-party tools such as ViewVC</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Master-slave server replication</entry>
            <entry>Transparent write-proxying available from slave to master</entry>
            <entry>Can only create read-only slave servers</entry>
            <entry>Can only create read-only slave servers</entry>
          </row>


          <row>
            <entry>Speed</entry>
            <entry>Somewhat slower</entry>
            <entry>Somewhat faster</entry>
            <entry>Somewhat faster</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Initial setup</entry>
            <entry>Somewhat complex</entry>
            <entry>Extremely simple</entry>
            <entry>Moderately simple</entry>
          </row>

        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="svn.serverconfig.choosing">

    <title>Choosing a Server Configuration</title>

    <para>So, which server should you use?  Which is best?</para>

    <para>Obviously, there's no right answer to that question.  Every
      team has different needs, and the different servers all
      represent different sets of trade-offs.  The Subversion project
      itself doesn't endorse one server or another, or consider either
      server more <quote>official</quote> than another.</para>

    <para>Here are some reasons why you might choose one deployment
      over another, as well as reasons you
      might <emphasis>not</emphasis> choose one.</para>

    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.choosing.svnserve">

      <title>The svnserve Server</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Why you might want to use it:</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>

            <listitem><para>Quick and easy to set
                up.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>Network protocol is stateful and
                noticeably faster than WebDAV.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>No need to create system accounts on
                server.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>Password is not passed over the
                network.</para></listitem>

            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Why you might want to avoid it:</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>

            <listitem><para>By default, only one authentication method
                is available, the network protocol is not encrypted,
                and the server stores clear text passwords.  (All these
                things can be changed by configuring SASL, but it's a
                bit more work to do.)</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>No logging of any kind, not even
                errors.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>No built-in web browsing.  (You'd have to
                install a separate web server and repository browsing software to
                add this.)</para></listitem>

            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.choosing.svn-ssh">

      <title>svnserve over SSH</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Why you might want to use it:</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>

            <listitem><para>The network protocol is stateful and
                noticeably faster than WebDAV.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>You can take advantage of existing SSH
                accounts and user infrastructure.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>All network traffic is
                encrypted.</para></listitem>

            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Why you might want to avoid it:</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>

            <listitem><para>Only one choice of authentication
                method is available.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>There is no logging of any kind, not even
                errors.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>It requires users to be in the same system group, or
                use a shared SSH key.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>If used improperly, it can lead to file permission
                problems.</para></listitem>

            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.choosing.apache">

      <title>The Apache HTTP Server</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Why you might want to use it:</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>

              <listitem><para>It allows Subversion to use any of the
                  numerous authentication systems already integrated
                  with Apache.</para></listitem>

              <listitem><para>There is no need to create system accounts on
                  the server.</para></listitem>

              <listitem><para>Full Apache logging is available.</para></listitem>

              <listitem><para>Network traffic can be encrypted via
                  SSL.</para></listitem>

              <listitem><para>HTTP(S) can usually go through corporate
                  firewalls.</para></listitem>

              <listitem><para>Built-in repository browsing is
                  available via web browser.</para></listitem>

              <listitem><para>The repository can be mounted as a network
                  drive for transparent version control (see
                  <xref
                  linkend="svn.webdav.autoversioning"/>).</para></listitem>

            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Why you might want to avoid it:</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>

            <listitem><para>Noticeably slower than
                <command>svnserve</command>, because HTTP is a
                stateless protocol and requires more network
                turnarounds.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>Initial setup can be complex.</para></listitem>

            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.choosing.recommendations">

      <title>Recommendations</title>

      <para>In general, the authors of this book recommend a vanilla
        <command>svnserve</command> installation for small teams just
        trying to get started with a Subversion server; it's the
        simplest to set up and has the fewest maintenance issues.
        You can always switch to a more complex server
        deployment as your needs change.</para>

      <para>Here are some general recommendations and tips, based on
        years of supporting users:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you're trying to set up the simplest possible
            server for your group, a
            vanilla <command>svnserve</command> installation is the
            easiest, fastest route.  Note, however, that your
            repository data will be transmitted in the clear over the
            network.  If your deployment is entirely within your
            company's LAN or VPN, this isn't an issue.  If the
            repository is exposed to the wide-open Internet, you
            might want to make sure that either the repository's
            contents aren't sensitive (e.g., it contains only
            open source code), or that you go the extra mile in
            configuring SASL to encrypt network communications.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you need to integrate with existing legacy identity
            systems (LDAP, Active Directory, NTLM, X.509, etc.),
            you must use either the Apache-based server
            or <command>svnserve</command> configured with SASL.  If
            you absolutely need server-side logs of either server
            errors or client activities, an Apache-based server
            is your only option.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           <para>If you've decided to use either Apache or stock
             <command>svnserve</command>, create a single
             <command>svn</command> user on your system and run the
             server process as that user.  Be sure to make the
             repository directory wholly owned by the
             <command>svn</command> user as well.  From a security
             point of view, this keeps the repository data nicely
             siloed and protected by operating system filesystem
             permissions, changeable by only the Subversion server
             process itself.</para> </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you have an existing infrastructure that is heavily based
            on SSH accounts, and if your users already have system
            accounts on your server machine, it makes sense to
            deploy an <command>svnserve</command>-over-SSH solution.
            Otherwise, we don't widely recommend this option to the
            public.  It's generally considered safer to have your
            users access the repository via (imaginary) accounts
            managed by <command>svnserve</command> or Apache, rather
            than by full-blown system accounts.  If your deep desire
            for encrypted communication still draws you to this
            option, we recommend using Apache with SSL or
            <command>svnserve</command> with SASL encryption
            instead.</para> </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> be seduced by the simple
            idea of having all of your users access a repository
            directly via <literal>file://</literal> URLs.  Even if the
            repository is readily available to everyone via a network
            share, this is a bad idea.  It removes any layers of
            protection between the users and the repository: users can
            accidentally (or intentionally) corrupt the repository
            database, it becomes hard to take the repository offline
            for inspection or upgrade, and it can lead to a mess of
            file permission problems (see <xref
            linkend="svn.serverconfig.multimethod"/>).  Note that this
            is also one of the reasons we warn against accessing
            repositories via <literal>svn+ssh://</literal>
            URLs&mdash;from a security standpoint, it's effectively
            the same as local users accessing via
            <literal>file://</literal>, and it can entail all the same
            problems if the administrator isn't careful.</para>
            </listitem> </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve">

    <title>svnserve, a Custom Server</title>

    <para>The <command>svnserve</command> program is a lightweight
      server, capable of speaking to clients over TCP/IP using a
      custom, stateful protocol.  Clients contact an
      <command>svnserve</command> server by using URLs that begin with
      the <literal>svn://</literal> or <literal>svn+ssh://</literal>
      scheme.  This section will explain the different ways of running
      <command>svnserve</command>, how clients authenticate themselves
      to the server, and how to configure appropriate access control
      to your repositories.</para>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.invoking">
      <title>Invoking the Server</title>

      <para>There are a few different ways to run the
        <command>svnserve</command> program:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Run <command>svnserve</command> as a
            standalone daemon, listening for
            requests.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Have the Unix <command>inetd</command> daemon
            temporarily spawn <command>svnserve</command> whenever a
            request comes in on a certain port.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Have SSH invoke a
            temporary <command>svnserve</command> over an encrypted
            tunnel.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Run <command>svnserve</command> as a Microsoft
            Windows service.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.invoking.daemon">
        <title>svnserve as daemon</title>

        <para>The easiest option is to run <command>svnserve</command>
          as a standalone <quote>daemon</quote> process.  Use the
          <option>-d</option> option for this:</para>

        <screen>
$ svnserve -d
$               # svnserve is now running, listening on port 3690
</screen>

        <para>When running <command>svnserve</command> in daemon mode,
          you can use the <option>--listen-port</option> and
          <option>--listen-host</option> options to customize the
          exact port and hostname to <quote>bind</quote> to.</para>

      <para>Once we successfully start <command>svnserve</command> as
        explained previously, it makes every repository on your system
        available to the network.  A client needs to specify an
        <emphasis>absolute</emphasis> path in the repository URL.  For
        example, if a repository is located at
        <filename>/var/svn/project1</filename>, a client would
        reach it via
        <uri>svn://host.example.com/var/svn/project1</uri>.  To
        increase security, you can pass the <option>-r</option> option
        to <command>svnserve</command>, which restricts it to
        exporting only repositories below that path.  For
        example:</para>
      
      <screen>
$ svnserve -d -r /var/svn
&hellip;
</screen>

      <para>Using the <option>-r</option> option effectively
        modifies the location that the program treats as the root of
        the remote filesystem space.  Clients then use URLs that
        have that path portion removed from them, leaving much
        shorter (and much less revealing) URLs:</para>

      <screen>
$ svn checkout svn://host.example.com/project1
&hellip;
</screen>

      </sect3>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.invoking.inetd">
        <title>svnserve via inetd</title>

        <para>If you want <command>inetd</command> to launch the
          process, you need to pass the <option>-i</option>
          (<option>--inetd</option>) option.  In the following
          example, we've shown the output from running
          <literal>svnserve -i</literal> at the command line, but note
          that this isn't how you actually start the daemon; see the
          paragraphs following the example for how to configure
          <command>inetd</command> to start
          <command>svnserve</command>.</para>

      <screen>
$ svnserve -i
( success ( 1 2 ( ANONYMOUS ) ( edit-pipeline ) ) )
</screen>

      <para>When invoked with the <option>--inetd</option> option,
        <command>svnserve</command> attempts to speak with a
        Subversion client via <filename>stdin</filename> and
        <filename>stdout</filename> using a custom protocol.  This is
        the standard behavior for a program being run via
        <command>inetd</command>.  The IANA has reserved port 3690 for
        the Subversion protocol, so on a Unix-like system you can add
        lines to <filename>/etc/services</filename> such as these (if
        they don't already exist):</para>

      <screen>
svn           3690/tcp   # Subversion
svn           3690/udp   # Subversion
</screen>

      <para>If your system is using a classic Unix-like
        <command>inetd</command> daemon, you can add this line to
        <filename>/etc/inetd.conf</filename>:</para>

      <screen>
svn stream tcp nowait svnowner /usr/bin/svnserve svnserve -i
</screen>

      <para>Make sure <quote>svnowner</quote> is a user that has
        appropriate permissions to access your repositories.  Now,
        when a client connection comes into your server on port 3690,
        <command>inetd</command> will spawn an
        <command>svnserve</command> process to service it.  Of course,
        you may also want to add <option>-r</option> to the
        configuration line as well, to restrict which repositories are
        exported.</para>

      </sect3>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.invoking.tunnel">
        <title>svnserve over a tunnel</title>

        <para>A third way to invoke <command>svnserve</command> is in
          tunnel mode, using the <option>-t</option> option.  This
          mode assumes that a remote-service program such as
          <command>rsh</command> or <command>ssh</command> has
          successfully authenticated a user and is now invoking a
          private <command>svnserve</command> process <emphasis>as
          that user</emphasis>.  (Note that you, the user, will
          rarely, if ever, have reason to invoke
          <command>svnserve</command> with the <option>-t</option> at
          the command line; instead, the SSH daemon
          does so for you.)  The <command>svnserve</command> program
          behaves normally (communicating via
          <filename>stdin</filename> and <filename>stdout</filename>)
          and assumes that the traffic is being automatically
          redirected over some sort of tunnel back to the client.
          When <command>svnserve</command> is invoked by a tunnel
          agent like this, be sure that the authenticated user has
          full read and write access to the repository database files.
          It's essentially the same as a local user accessing the
          repository via <literal>file://</literal> URLs.</para>

        <para>This option is described in much more detail later in
          this chapter in <xref
          linkend="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.sshauth"/>.</para>

      </sect3>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.invoking.winservice">
        <title>svnserve as Windows service</title>

        <para>If your Windows system is a descendant of Windows NT
          (2000, 2003, XP, or Vista), you can
          run <command>svnserve</command> as a standard Windows
          service.  This is typically a much nicer experience than
          running it as a standalone daemon with the <option>--daemon
          (-d)</option> option.  Using daemon mode requires launching
          a console, typing a command, and then leaving the console
          window running indefinitely.  A Windows service, however,
          runs in the background, can start at boot time
          automatically, and can be started and stopped using the same
          consistent administration interface as other
          Windows services. </para>

        <para>You'll need to define the new service using the
          command-line tool <command>SC.EXE</command>.  Much like
          the <command>inetd</command> configuration line, you must
          specify an exact invocation of <command>svnserve</command>
          for Windows to run at startup time:</para>

        <screen>
C:\&gt; sc create svn
        binpath= "C:\svn\bin\svnserve.exe --service -r C:\repos"
        displayname= "Subversion Server"
        depend= Tcpip
        start= auto
</screen>

        <para>This defines a new Windows service named
          <quote>svn,</quote> which executes a particular
          <command>svnserve.exe</command> command when started (in
          this case, rooted at <filename>C:\repos</filename>).  There
          are a number of caveats in the prior example,
          however.</para>

        <para>First, notice that the <command>svnserve.exe</command>
          program must always be invoked with the
          <option>--service</option> option.  Any other options to
          <command>svnserve</command> must then be specified on the
          same line, but you cannot add conflicting options such as
          <option>--daemon (-d)</option>, <option>--tunnel</option>,
          or <option>--inetd (-i)</option>.  Options such as
          <option>-r</option> or <option>--listen-port</option> are
          fine, though.  Second, be careful about spaces when invoking
          the <command>SC.EXE</command> command: the <literal>key=
          value</literal> patterns must have no spaces between
          <literal>key=</literal> and must have exactly one space
          before the <literal>value</literal>.  Lastly, be careful
          about spaces in your command line to be invoked.  If a
          directory name contains spaces (or other characters that
          need escaping), place the entire inner value of
          <literal>binpath</literal> in double quotes, by escaping
          them:</para>

        <screen>
C:\&gt; sc create svn
        binpath= "\"C:\program files\svn\bin\svnserve.exe\" --service -r C:\repos"
        displayname= "Subversion Server"
        depend= Tcpip
        start= auto
</screen>

        <para>Also note that the word <literal>binpath</literal> is
          misleading&mdash;its value is a <emphasis>command
          line</emphasis>, not the path to an executable.  That's why
          you need to surround it with quotes if it contains
          embedded spaces.</para>

        <para>Once the service is defined, it can be stopped, started,
          or queried using standard GUI tools (the Services
          administrative control panel), or at the command
          line:</para>

        <screen>
C:\&gt; net stop svn
C:\&gt; net start svn
</screen>

        <para>The service can also be uninstalled (i.e., undefined) by
          deleting its definition:  <userinput>sc delete svn</userinput>.
          Just be sure to stop the service first!
          The <command>SC.EXE</command> program has many other
          subcommands and options; run <userinput>sc /?</userinput> to
          learn more about it.</para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.auth">
      <title>Built-in Authentication and Authorization</title>

      <para>When a client connects to an <command>svnserve</command>
        process, the following things happen:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>The client selects a specific
        repository.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>The server processes the repository's
        <filename>conf/svnserve.conf</filename> file and begins to
        enforce any authentication and authorization policies it
        describes.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>Depending on the defined policies, one of the
        following may occur:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>The client may be allowed to make requests
              anonymously, without ever receiving an authentication
              challenge.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>The client may be challenged for
              authentication at any time.</para></listitem>

            <listitem><para>If operating in tunnel mode, the client
              will declare itself to be already externally
              authenticated (typically by SSH).</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The <command>svnserve</command> server, by default, knows
        only how to send a CRAM-MD5
        <footnote>
          <para>See RFC 2195.</para>
        </footnote>
        authentication challenge.  In essence,
        the server sends a small amount of data to the client.  The
        client uses the MD5 hash algorithm to create a fingerprint of
        the data and password combined, and then sends the fingerprint
        as a response.  The server performs the same computation with
        the stored password to verify that the result is identical.
        <emphasis>At no point does the actual password travel over the
        network.</emphasis></para>

      <para>If your <command>svnserve</command> server was built with
        SASL support, it not only knows how to send CRAM-MD5 challenges,
        but also likely knows a whole host of other authentication
        mechanisms.  See <xref
        linkend="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.sasl"/> later in this
        chapter to learn how to configure SASL authentication and
        encryption.</para>

      <para>It's also possible, of course, for the client to be
        externally authenticated via a tunnel agent, such as
        <command>ssh</command>.  In that case, the server simply
        examines the user it's running as, and uses this name as the
        authenticated username.  For more on this, see the later
        section, <xref
        linkend="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.sshauth"/>.</para>

      <para>As you've already guessed, a repository's
        <filename>svnserve.conf</filename> file is the central
        mechanism for controlling authentication and authorization
        policies.  The file has the same format as other configuration
        files (see <xref linkend="svn.advanced.confarea"/>):
        section names are marked by square brackets
        (<literal>[</literal> and <literal>]</literal>), comments
        begin with hashes (<literal>#</literal>), and each section
        contains specific variables that can be set (<literal>variable
        = value</literal>).  Let's walk through these files and learn
        how to use them.</para>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.auth.users">
        <title>Create a users file and realm</title>

        <para>For now, the <literal>[general]</literal> section of
          <filename>svnserve.conf</filename> has all the variables you
          need.  Begin by changing the values of those variables:
          choose a name for a file that will contain your usernames
          and passwords and choose an authentication realm:</para>

        <screen>
[general]
password-db = userfile
realm = example realm
</screen>

        <para>The <literal>realm</literal> is a name that you define.
          It tells clients which sort of <quote>authentication
          namespace</quote> they're connecting to; the Subversion
          client displays it in the authentication prompt and uses it
          as a key (along with the server's hostname and port) for
          caching credentials on disk (see <xref
          linkend="svn.serverconfig.netmodel.credcache"/>).  The
          <literal>password-db</literal> variable points to a separate
          file that contains a list of usernames and passwords, using
          the same familiar format.  For example:</para>

        <screen>
[users]
harry = foopassword
sally = barpassword
</screen>

        <para>The value of <literal>password-db</literal> can be an
          absolute or relative path to the users file.  For many
          admins, it's easy to keep the file right in the
          <filename>conf/</filename> area of the repository, alongside
          <filename>svnserve.conf</filename>.  On the other hand, it's
          possible you may want to have two or more repositories share
          the same users file; in that case, the file should probably
          live in a more public place.  The repositories sharing the
          users file should also be configured to have the same realm,
          since the list of users essentially defines an
          authentication realm.  Wherever the file lives, be sure to
          set the file's read and write permissions appropriately.  If
          you know which user(s) <command>svnserve</command> will run
          as, restrict read access to the users file as necessary.</para>

      </sect3>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.auth.general">
        <title>Set access controls</title>

        <para>There are two more variables to set in the
          <filename>svnserve.conf</filename> file: they determine what
          unauthenticated (anonymous) and authenticated users are
          allowed to do.  The variables <literal>anon-access</literal>
          and <literal>auth-access</literal> can be set to the value
          <literal>none</literal>, <literal>read</literal>, or
          <literal>write</literal>.  Setting the value to
          <literal>none</literal> prohibits both reading and writing;
          <literal>read</literal> allows read-only access to the
          repository, and <literal>write</literal> allows complete
          read/write access to the repository.  For example:</para>

        <screen>
[general]
password-db = userfile
realm = example realm

# anonymous users can only read the repository
anon-access = read

# authenticated users can both read and write
auth-access = write
</screen>

        <para>The example settings are, in fact, the default values of
          the variables, should you forget to define them.  If you
          want to be even more conservative, you can block anonymous
          access completely:</para>

        <screen>
[general]
password-db = userfile
realm = example realm

# anonymous users aren't allowed
anon-access = none

# authenticated users can both read and write
auth-access = write
</screen>

        <para>The server process understands not only
        these <quote>blanket</quote> access controls to the
        repository, but also finer-grained access restrictions placed
        on specific files and directories within the repository.  To
        make use of this feature, you need to define a file containing
        more detailed rules, and then set
        the <literal>authz-db</literal> variable to point to it:</para>

        <screen>
[general]
password-db = userfile
realm = example realm

# Specific access rules for specific locations
authz-db = authzfile
</screen>

        <para>We discuss the syntax of the <filename>authzfile</filename> file
          in detail later in this chapter, in
          <xref linkend="svn.serverconfig.pathbasedauthz"/>.  Note
          that the <literal>authz-db</literal> variable isn't mutually
          exclusive with the <literal>anon-access</literal>
          and <literal>auth-access</literal> variables;  if all the
          variables are defined at once, <emphasis>all</emphasis>
          of the rules must be satisfied before access is allowed.</para>

      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.sasl">
      <title>Using <command>svnserve</command> with SASL</title>

      <para>For many teams, the built-in CRAM-MD5 authentication is
        all they need from <command>svnserve</command>.  However, if
        your server (and your Subversion clients) were built with the
        Cyrus Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) library,
        you have a number of authentication and encryption
        options available to you.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title>What Is SASL?</title>
        <para>The Cyrus Simple Authentication and Security Layer is
          open source software written by Carnegie Mellon University.
          It adds generic authentication and encryption capabilities
          to any network protocol, and as of Subversion 1.5 and later,
          both the <command>svnserve</command> server
          and <command>svn</command> client know how to make use of
          this library.  It may or may not be available to you: if
          you're building Subversion yourself, you'll need to have at
          least version 2.1 of SASL installed on your system, and
          you'll need to make sure that it's detected during
          Subversion's build process.  If you're using a prebuilt
          Subversion binary package, you'll have to check with the
          package maintainer as to whether SASL support was compiled
          in.  SASL comes with a number of pluggable modules that
          represent different authentication systems: Kerberos
          (GSSAPI), NTLM, One-Time-Passwords (OTP), DIGEST-MD5, LDAP,
          Secure-Remote-Password (SRP), and others.  Certain
          mechanisms may or may not be available to you; be sure to
          check which modules are provided.</para>

        <para>You can download Cyrus SASL (both code and
          documentation) from
          <ulink url="http://asg.web.cmu.edu/sasl/sasl-library.html"/>.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <para>Normally, when a subversion client connects to
        <command>svnserve</command>, the server sends a greeting that
        advertises a list of the capabilities it supports, and the
        client responds with a similar list of capabilities.  If the
        server is configured to require authentication, it then sends
        a challenge that lists the authentication mechanisms
        available; the client responds by choosing one of the
        mechanisms, and then authentication is carried out in some
        number of round-trip messages.  Even when SASL capabilities
        aren't present, the client and server inherently know how to
        use the CRAM-MD5 and ANONYMOUS mechanisms (see
        <xref linkend="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.auth"/>).  If server
        and client were linked against SASL, a number of other
        authentication mechanisms may also be available.  However,
        you'll need to explicitly configure SASL on the server side to
        advertise them.</para>

      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.sasl.authn">
        <title>Authenticating with SASL</title>

        <para>To activate specific SASL mechanisms on the server,
          you'll need to do two things.  First, create
          a <literal>[sasl]</literal> section in your
          repository's <filename>svnserve.conf</filename> file with an
          initial key-value pair:</para>

        <programlisting>
          [sasl]
          use-sasl = true
</programlisting>

        <para>Second, create a main SASL configuration file
          called <filename>svn.conf</filename> in a place where the
          SASL library can find it&mdash;typically in the directory
          where SASL plug-ins are located.  You'll have to locate the
          plug-in directory on your particular system, such
          as <filename>/usr/lib/sasl2/</filename>
          or <filename>/etc/sasl2/</filename>.  (Note that this
          is <emphasis>not</emphasis>
          the <filename>svnserve.conf</filename> file that lives
          within a repository!)</para>

        <para>On a Windows server, you'll also have to edit the system
          registry (using a tool such as <command>regedit</command>)
          to tell SASL where to find things.  Create a registry key
          named <literal>[HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Carnegie
          Mellon\Project Cyrus\SASL Library]</literal>, and place two
          keys inside it: a key called <literal>SearchPath</literal>
          (whose value is a path to the directory containing the SASL
          <filename>sasl*.dll</filename> plug-in libraries), and a key
          called
          <literal>ConfFile</literal> (whose value is a path to the
          parent directory containing
          the <filename>svn.conf</filename> file you created).</para>

        <para>Because SASL provides so many different kinds of
          authentication mechanisms, it would be foolish (and far
          beyond the scope of this book) to try to describe every
          possible server-side configuration.  Instead, we recommend
          that you read the documentation supplied in the
          <filename>doc/</filename> subdirectory of the SASL source
          code.  It goes into great detail about every mechanism and
          how to configure the server appropriately for each.  For the
          purposes of this discussion, we'll just demonstrate a simple
          example of configuring the DIGEST-MD5 mechanism.  For
          example, if your <filename>subversion.conf</filename>
          (or <filename>svn.conf</filename>) file contains the
          following:</para>

        <screen>
pwcheck_method: auxprop
auxprop_plugin: sasldb
sasldb_path: /etc/my_sasldb
mech_list: DIGEST-MD5
</screen>

        <para>you've told SASL to advertise the DIGEST-MD5
          mechanism to clients and to check user passwords against a
          private password database located
          at <filename>/etc/my_sasldb</filename>.  A system
          administrator can then use
          the <command>saslpasswd2</command> program to add or modify
          usernames and passwords in the database:</para>

        <screen>
$ saslpasswd2 -c -f /etc/my_sasldb -u realm username
</screen>

        <para>A few words of warning: first, make sure the
          <quote>realm</quote> argument
          to <command>saslpasswd2</command> matches the same realm
          you've defined in your
          repository's <filename>svnserve.conf</filename> file; if
          they don't match, authentication will fail.  Also, due to a
          shortcoming in SASL, the common realm must be a string with
          no space characters.  Finally, if you decide to go with the
          standard SASL password database, make sure
          the <command>svnserve</command> program has read access to
          the file (and possibly write access as well, if you're using
          a mechanism such as OTP).</para>

        <para>This is just one simple way of configuring SASL.  Many
          other authentication mechanisms are available, and passwords
          can be stored in other places such as in LDAP or a SQL
          database.  Consult the full SASL documentation for
          details.</para>

        <para>Remember that if you configure your server to only allow
          certain SASL authentication mechanisms, this forces all
          connecting clients to have SASL support as well.  Any
          Subversion client built without SASL support (which includes
          all pre-1.5 clients) will be unable to authenticate.  On the
          one hand, this sort of restriction may be exactly what you
          want (<quote>My clients must all use Kerberos!</quote>).
          However, if you still want non-SASL clients to be able to
          authenticate, be sure to advertise the CRAM-MD5 mechanism as
          an option.  All clients are able to use CRAM-MD5, whether
          they have SASL capabilities or not.</para>

        </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.sasl.encryption">
        <title>SASL encryption</title>

        <para>SASL is also able to perform data encryption if a
          particular mechanism supports it.  The built-in CRAM-MD5
          mechanism doesn't support encryption, but DIGEST-MD5 does,
          and mechanisms such as SRP actually require use of the
          OpenSSL library.  To enable or disable different levels of
          encryption, you can set two values in your repository's
          <filename>svnserve.conf</filename> file:</para>

        <screen>
[sasl]
use-sasl = true
min-encryption = 128
max-encryption = 256
</screen>

        <para>The <literal>min-encryption</literal> and
          <literal>max-encryption</literal> variables control the
          level of encryption demanded by the server.  To disable
          encryption completely, set both values to 0.  To enable
          simple checksumming of data (i.e., prevent tampering and
          guarantee data integrity without encryption), set both
          values to 1.  If you wish to allow&mdash;but not
          require&mdash;encryption, set the minimum value to 0, and
          the maximum value to some bit length.  To require encryption
          unconditionally, set both values to numbers greater than 1.
          In our previous example, we require clients to do at least
          128-bit encryption, but no more than 256-bit
          encryption.</para>

        </sect3>

      </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.sshauth">
      <title>Tunneling over SSH</title>

      <para><command>svnserve</command>'s built-in authentication (and
        SASL support) can be very handy, because it avoids the need to
        create real system accounts.  On the other hand, some
        administrators already have well-established SSH
        authentication frameworks in place.  In these situations, all
        of the project's users already have system accounts and the
        ability to <quote>SSH into</quote> the server machine.</para>

      <para>It's easy to use SSH in conjunction with
        <command>svnserve</command>.  The client simply uses the
        <literal>svn+ssh://</literal> URL scheme to connect:</para>

      <screen>
$ whoami
harry

$ svn list svn+ssh://host.example.com/repos/project
harryssh@host.example.com's password:  *****

foo
bar
baz
&hellip;
</screen>

      <para>In this example, the Subversion client is invoking a local
        <command>ssh</command> process, connecting to
        <literal>host.example.com</literal>, authenticating as the
        user <literal>harryssh</literal> (according to SSH user
        configuration), then spawning a private
        <command>svnserve</command> process on the remote machine
        running as the user <literal>harryssh</literal>.  The
        <command>svnserve</command> command is being invoked in tunnel
        mode (<option>-t</option>), and its network protocol is being
        <quote>tunneled</quote> over the encrypted connection by
        <command>ssh</command>, the tunnel agent.
        If the client performs a commit, the authenticated username
        <literal>harryssh</literal> will be used as the author
        of the new revision.</para>

      <para>The important thing to understand here is that the
        Subversion client is <emphasis>not</emphasis> connecting to a
        running <command>svnserve</command> daemon.  This method of
        access doesn't require a daemon, nor does it notice one if
        present.  It relies wholly on the ability of
        <command>ssh</command> to spawn a temporary
        <command>svnserve</command> process, which then terminates
        when the network connection is closed.</para>

      <para>When using <literal>svn+ssh://</literal> URLs to access a
        repository, remember that it's the <command>ssh</command>
        program prompting for authentication, and
        <emphasis>not</emphasis> the <command>svn</command> client
        program.  That means there's no automatic password-caching
        going on (see <xref linkend="svn.serverconfig.netmodel.credcache"/>).  The
        Subversion client often makes multiple connections to the
        repository, though users don't normally notice this due to the
        password caching feature.  When using
        <literal>svn+ssh://</literal> URLs, however, users may be
        annoyed by <command>ssh</command> repeatedly asking for a
        password for every outbound connection.  The solution is to
        use a separate SSH password-caching tool such as
        <command>ssh-agent</command> on a Unix-like system, or
        <command>pageant</command> on Windows.</para>

      <para>When running over a tunnel, authorization is primarily
        controlled by operating system permissions to the repository's
        database files; it's very much the same as if Harry were
        accessing the repository directly via a
        <literal>file://</literal> URL.  If multiple system users are
        going to be accessing the repository directly, you may want to
        place them into a common group, and you'll need to be careful
        about umasks (be sure to read <xref
        linkend="svn.serverconfig.multimethod"/> later in this
        chapter).  But even in the case of tunneling, you can still use the
        <filename>svnserve.conf</filename> file to block access, by
        simply setting <literal>auth-access = read</literal>
        or <literal>auth-access = none</literal>.
        <footnote>
          <para>Note that using any sort of
            <command>svnserve</command>-enforced access control at all
            is a bit pointless; the user already has direct access to
            the repository database.</para>
        </footnote>
      </para>

      <para>You'd think that the story of SSH tunneling would end
        here, but it doesn't.  Subversion allows you to create custom
        tunnel behaviors in your runtime <filename>config</filename>
        file (see <xref linkend="svn.advanced.confarea"/>.)  For
        example, suppose you want to use RSH instead of SSH.
        <footnote>
          <para>We don't actually recommend this, since RSH
            is notably less secure than SSH.</para>
        </footnote>
        In the <literal>[tunnels]</literal> section of your
        <filename>config</filename> file, simply define it like
        this:</para>

      <screen>
[tunnels]
rsh = rsh
</screen>

      <para>And now, you can use this new tunnel definition by using a
        URL scheme that matches the name of your new variable:
        <literal>svn+rsh://host/path</literal>.  When using the new
        URL scheme, the Subversion client will actually be running the
        command <userinput>rsh host svnserve -t</userinput> behind the
        scenes.  If you include a username in the URL (e.g.,
        <literal>svn+rsh://username@host/path</literal>), the client
        will also include that in its command (<userinput>rsh
        username@host svnserve -t</userinput>).  But you can define new
        tunneling schemes to be much more clever than that:</para>

      <screen>
[tunnels]
joessh = $JOESSH /opt/alternate/ssh -p 29934
</screen>

      <para>This example demonstrates a couple of things.  First, it
        shows how to make the Subversion client launch a very specific
        tunneling binary (the one located at
        <filename>/opt/alternate/ssh</filename>) with specific
        options.  In this case, accessing an
        <literal>svn+joessh://</literal> URL would invoke the
        particular SSH binary with <option>-p 29934</option> as
        arguments&mdash;useful if you want the tunnel program to
        connect to a nonstandard port.</para>

      <para>Second, it shows how to define a custom environment
        variable that can override the name of the tunneling program.
        Setting the <literal>SVN_SSH</literal> environment variable is
        a convenient way to override the default SSH tunnel agent.
        But if you need to have several different overrides for
        different servers, each perhaps contacting a different port or
        passing a different set of options to SSH, you can use the
        mechanism demonstrated in this example.  Now if we were to set
        the <literal>JOESSH</literal> environment variable, its value
        would override the entire value of the tunnel
        variable&mdash;<command>$JOESSH</command> would be executed
        instead of <userinput>/opt/alternate/ssh -p
        29934</userinput>.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.sshtricks">
      <title>SSH configuration tricks</title>

      <para>It's possible to control not only the way in which the
        client invokes <command>ssh</command>, but also to control
        the behavior of <command>sshd</command> on your server
        machine.  In this section, we'll show how to control the
        exact <command>svnserve</command> command executed
        by <command>sshd</command>, as well as how to have multiple
        users share a single system account.</para>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.sshtricks.setup">
        <title>Initial setup</title>

        <para>To begin, locate the home directory of the account
          you'll be using to launch <command>svnserve</command>.  Make
          sure the account has an SSH public/private keypair
          installed, and that the user can log in via public-key
          authentication.  Password authentication will not work,
          since all of the following SSH tricks revolve around using
          the SSH <filename>authorized_keys</filename> file.</para>

        <para>If it doesn't already exist, create the
          <filename>authorized_keys</filename> file (on Unix,
          typically <filename>~/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename>).
          Each line in this file describes a public key that is
          allowed to connect.  The lines are typically of the
          form:</para>

        <screen>
  ssh-dsa AAAABtce9euch&hellip; user@example.com
</screen>

        <para>The first field describes the type of key, the second
          field is the base64-encoded key itself, and the third field
          is a comment.  However, it's a lesser known fact that the
          entire line can be preceded by a <literal>command</literal>
          field:</para>

        <screen>
  command="program" ssh-dsa AAAABtce9euch&hellip; user@example.com
</screen>

        <para>When the <literal>command</literal> field is set, the
          SSH daemon will run the named program instead of the
          typical tunnel-mode <command>svnserve</command> invocation that the
          Subversion client asks for.  This opens the door to a number
          of server-side tricks.  In the following examples, we
          abbreviate the lines of the file as:</para>

        <screen>
  command="program" TYPE KEY COMMENT
</screen>

      </sect3>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.svnserve.sshtricks.fixedcmd">
        <title>Controlling the invoked command</title>

        <para>Because we can specify the executed server-side command,
          it's easy to name a specific <command>svnserve</command>
          binary to run and to pass it extra arguments:</para>

        <screen>
  command="/path/to/svnserve -t -r /virtual/root" TYPE KEY COMMENT
</screen>

        <para>In this example, <filename>/path/to/svnserve</filename>
          might be a custom wrapper script
          around <command>svnserve</command> which sets the umask (see
          <xref linkend="svn.serverconfig.multimethod"/>.)  It also
          shows how to anchor <command>svnserve</command> in a virtual
          root directory, just as one often does when
          running <command>svnserve</command> as a daemon process.
          This might be done either to restrict access to parts of the
          system, or simply to relieve the user of having to type an
          absolute path in the <literal>svn+ssh://</literal>
          URL.</para>

        <para>It's also possible to have multiple users share a single
          account.  Instead of creating a separate system account for
          each user, generate a public/private key pair for each
          person.  Then place each public key into
          the <filename>authorized_users</filename> file, one per
          line, and use the <option>--tunnel-user</option>
          option:</para>

        <screen>
  command="svnserve -t --tunnel-user=harry" TYPE1 KEY1 harry@example.com
  command="svnserve -t --tunnel-user=sally" TYPE2 KEY2 sally@example.com
</screen>

        <para>This example allows both Harry and Sally to connect to
          the same account via public key authentication.  Each of
          them has a custom command that will be executed;
          the <option>--tunnel-user</option> option 
          tells <command>svnserve</command> to assume that the named
          argument is the authenticated user.  Without
          <option>--tunnel-user</option>, it would appear as though
          all commits were coming from the one shared system
          account.</para>

        <para>A final word of caution: giving a user access to the
          server via public-key in a shared account might still allow
          other forms of SSH access, even if you've set
          the <literal>command</literal> value
          in <filename>authorized_keys</filename>.  For example, the
          user may still get shell access through SSH or be able to
          perform X11 or general port forwarding through your server.
          To give the user as little permission as possible, you may
          want to specify a number of restrictive options immediately
          after the <literal>command</literal>:</para>

        <screen>
  command="svnserve -t --tunnel-user=harry",no-port-forwarding,no-agent-forw
arding,no-X11-forwarding,no-pty TYPE1 KEY1 harry@example.com
</screen>

        <para>Note that this all must be on one line&mdash;truly on
          one line&mdash;since SSH <filename>authorized_keys</filename> 
          files do not even allow the conventional backslash character
          (<literal>\</literal>) for line continuation.  The only
          reason we've shown it with a line break is to fit it on
          the physical page of a book.</para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>


  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd">

    <title>httpd, the Apache HTTP Server</title>

    <para>The Apache HTTP Server is a <quote>heavy-duty</quote>
      network server that Subversion can leverage.  Via a custom
      module, <command>httpd</command> makes Subversion repositories
      available to clients via the WebDAV/DeltaV protocol, which is an
      extension to HTTP 1.1 (see <ulink url="http://www.webdav.org/"/>
      for more information).  This protocol takes the ubiquitous HTTP
      protocol that is the core of the World Wide Web, and adds
      writing&mdash;specifically, versioned
      writing&mdash;capabilities.  The result is a standardized,
      robust system that is conveniently packaged as part of the
      Apache 2.0 software, supported by numerous operating systems
      and third-party products, and doesn't require network
      administrators to open up yet another custom port.
      <footnote>
        <para>They really hate doing that.</para>
      </footnote>
      While an Apache-Subversion server has more features than
      <command>svnserve</command>, it's also a bit more difficult
      to set up.  With flexibility often comes more complexity.</para>

    <para>Much of the following discussion includes references to
      Apache configuration directives.  While some examples are given
      of the use of these directives, describing them in full is
      outside the scope of this chapter.  The Apache team maintains
      excellent documentation, publicly available on their web site at
      <ulink url="http://httpd.apache.org"/>.  For example, a general
      reference for the configuration directives is located at
      <ulink url="
      http://httpd.apache.org/docs-2.0/mod/directives.html"/>.</para>

    <para>Also, as you make changes to your Apache setup, it is likely
      that somewhere along the way a mistake will be made.  If you are
      not already familiar with Apache's logging subsystem, you should
      become aware of it.  In your <filename>httpd.conf</filename>
      file are directives that specify the on-disk locations of the
      access and error logs generated by Apache (the
      <literal>CustomLog</literal> and <literal>ErrorLog</literal>
      directives, respectively).
      Subversion's <command>mod_dav_svn</command> uses Apache's error
      logging interface as well.  You can always browse the contents
      of those files for information that might reveal the source of a
      problem that is not clearly noticeable otherwise.</para>

    <sidebar>
      <title>Why Apache 2?</title>

      <para>If you're a system administrator, it's very likely that
        you're already running the Apache web server and have some
        prior experience with it.  At the time of this writing, Apache 1.3
        is the more popular version of Apache.  The world has
        been somewhat slow to upgrade to the Apache 2.x series for
        various reasons: some people fear change, especially changing
        something as critical as a web server.  Other people depend on
        plug-in modules that work only against the Apache 1.3 API, and
        they are waiting for a 2.x port.  Whatever the reason, many
        people begin to worry when they first discover that
        Subversion's Apache module is written specifically for the
        Apache 2 API.</para>

      <para>The proper response to this problem is: don't worry about
        it.  It's easy to run Apache 1.3 and Apache 2 side by side;
        simply install them to separate places and use Apache 2 as a
        dedicated Subversion server that runs on a port other than 80.
        Clients can access the repository by placing the port number
        into the URL:</para>

      <screen>
$ svn checkout http://host.example.com:7382/repos/project
</screen>
    </sidebar>


    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.prereqs">
      <title>Prerequisites</title>

      <para>To network your repository over HTTP, you basically need
        four components, available in two packages.  You'll need
        Apache <command>httpd</command> 2.0, the
        <command>mod_dav</command> DAV module that comes with it,
        Subversion, and the <command>mod_dav_svn</command>
        filesystem provider module distributed with Subversion.
        Once you have all of those components, the process of
        networking your repository is as simple as:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Getting httpd 2.0 up and running with
            the <command>mod_dav</command> module</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Installing the <command>mod_dav_svn</command> backend
            to <command>mod_dav</command>, which uses Subversion's
            libraries to access the repository</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Configuring your <filename>httpd.conf</filename>
            file to export (or expose) the repository</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>You can accomplish the first two items either by
        compiling <command>httpd</command> and Subversion from
        source code or by installing prebuilt binary packages of
        them on your system.  For the most up-to-date information on
        how to compile Subversion for use with the Apache HTTP Server,
        as well as how to compile and configure Apache itself for
        this purpose, see the <filename>INSTALL</filename> file in
        the top level of the Subversion source code tree.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.basic">
      <title>Basic Apache Configuration</title>

      <para>Once you have all the necessary components installed on
        your system, all that remains is the configuration of Apache
        via its <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file.  Instruct Apache
        to load the <command>mod_dav_svn</command> module using the
        <literal>LoadModule</literal> directive.  This directive must
        precede any other Subversion-related configuration items.  If
        your Apache was installed using the default layout, your
        <command>mod_dav_svn</command> module should have been
        installed in the <filename>modules</filename> subdirectory of
        the Apache install location (often
        <filename>/usr/local/apache2</filename>).  The
        <literal>LoadModule</literal> directive has a simple syntax,
        mapping a named module to the location of a shared library on
        disk:</para>

        <screen>
LoadModule dav_svn_module     modules/mod_dav_svn.so
</screen>

      <para>Note that if <command>mod_dav</command> was compiled as a
        shared object (instead of statically linked directly to the
        <command>httpd</command> binary), you'll need a similar
        <literal>LoadModule</literal> statement for it, too.  Be sure
        that it comes before the <command>mod_dav_svn</command> line:</para>

        <screen>
LoadModule dav_module         modules/mod_dav.so
LoadModule dav_svn_module     modules/mod_dav_svn.so
</screen>


      <para>At a later location in your configuration file, you now
        need to tell Apache where you keep your Subversion repository
        (or repositories).  The <literal>Location</literal> directive
        has an XML-like notation, starting with an opening tag and
        ending with a closing tag, with various other configuration
        directives in the middle.  The purpose of the
        <literal>Location</literal> directive is to instruct Apache to
        do something special when handling requests that are directed
        at a given URL or one of its children.  In the case of
        Subversion, you want Apache to simply hand off support for
        URLs that point at versioned resources to the DAV layer.  You
        can instruct Apache to delegate the handling of all URLs whose
        path portions (the part of the URL that follows the server's
        name and the optional port number) begin with
        <filename>/repos/</filename> to a DAV provider whose
        repository is located at
        <filename>/var/svn/repository</filename> using the
        following <filename>httpd.conf</filename> syntax:</para>

        <screen>
&lt;Location /repos&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNPath /var/svn/repository
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

      <para>If you plan to support multiple Subversion repositories
        that will reside in the same parent directory on your local
        disk, you can use an alternative
        directive&mdash;<literal>SVNParentPath</literal>&mdash;to
        indicate that common parent directory.  For example, if you
        know you will be creating multiple Subversion repositories in
        a directory <filename>/var/svn</filename> that would be
        accessed via URLs such as
        <uri>http://my.server.com/svn/repos1</uri>,
        <uri>http://my.server.com/svn/repos2</uri>, and so on, you
        could use the <filename>httpd.conf</filename> configuration
        syntax in the following example:</para>

        <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn

  # any "/svn/foo" URL will map to a repository /var/svn/foo
  SVNParentPath /var/svn
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

      <para>Using the previous syntax, Apache will delegate the
        handling of all URLs whose path portions begin with
        <filename>/svn/</filename> to the Subversion DAV provider,
        which will then assume that any items in the directory
        specified by the <literal>SVNParentPath</literal> directive
        are actually Subversion repositories.  This is a particularly
        convenient syntax in that, unlike the use of the
        <literal>SVNPath</literal> directive, you don't have to
        restart Apache to create and network new repositories.</para>

      <para>Be sure that when you define your new
        <literal>Location</literal>, it doesn't overlap with other
        exported locations.  For example, if your main
        <literal>DocumentRoot</literal> is exported to
        <filename>/www</filename>, do not export a Subversion
        repository in <literal>&lt;Location /www/repos&gt;</literal>.
        If a request comes in for the URI
        <filename>/www/repos/foo.c</filename>, Apache won't know
        whether to look for a file <filename>repos/foo.c</filename> in
        the <literal>DocumentRoot</literal>, or whether to delegate
        <command>mod_dav_svn</command> to return
        <filename>foo.c</filename> from the Subversion repository.
        The result is often an error from the server of the form
        <literal>301 Moved Permanently</literal>.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title>Server Names and the COPY Request</title>

        <para>Subversion makes use of the <literal>COPY</literal>
          request type to perform server-side copies of files and
          directories.  As part of the sanity checking done by the
          Apache modules, the source of the copy is expected to be
          located on the same machine as the destination of the copy.
          To satisfy this requirement, you might need to
          tell <command>mod_dav</command> the name you use as the
          hostname of your server.  Generally, you can use
          the <literal>ServerName</literal> directive in
          <filename>httpd.conf</filename> to accomplish this.</para>

        <screen>
ServerName svn.example.com
</screen>

        <para>If you are using Apache's virtual hosting support via
          the <literal>NameVirtualHost</literal> directive, you may
          need to use the <literal>ServerAlias</literal> directive to
          specify additional names by which your server is known.
          Again, refer to the Apache documentation for full
          details.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <para>At this stage, you should strongly consider the question
        of permissions.  If you've been running Apache for some time
        now as your regular web server, you probably already have a
        collection of content&mdash;web pages, scripts, and such.
        These items have already been configured with a set of
        permissions that allows them to work with Apache, or more
        appropriately, that allows Apache to work with those files.
        Apache, when used as a Subversion server, will also need the
        correct permissions to read and write to your Subversion
        repository.</para>

      <para>You will need to determine a permission system setup that
        satisfies Subversion's requirements without messing up any
        previously existing web page or script installations.  This
        might mean changing the permissions on your Subversion
        repository to match those in use by other things that Apache
        serves for you, or it could mean using the
        <literal>User</literal> and <literal>Group</literal>
        directives in <filename>httpd.conf</filename> to specify that
        Apache should run as the user and group that owns your
        Subversion repository.  There is no single correct way to set
        up your permissions, and each administrator will have
        different reasons for doing things a certain way.  Just be
        aware that permission-related problems are perhaps the most
        common oversight when configuring a Subversion repository for
        use with Apache.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authn">
      <title>Authentication Options</title>

      <para>At this point, if you configured
        <filename>httpd.conf</filename> to contain something such as the
        following:</para>

      <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

      <para>your repository is <quote>anonymously</quote>
        accessible to the world.  Until you configure some
        authentication and authorization policies, the Subversion
        repositories that you make available via the
        <literal>Location</literal> directive will be generally
        accessible to everyone.  In other words:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Anyone can use a Subversion client to check out a
            working copy of a repository URL (or any of its
            subdirectories).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Anyone can interactively browse the repository's
            latest revision simply by pointing a web browser to
            the repository URL.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Anyone can commit to the repository.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Of course, you might have already set up
        a <filename>pre-commit</filename> hook script to prevent
        commits (see <xref linkend="svn.reposadmin.create.hooks"/>).
        But as you read on, you'll see that it's also possible to use
        Apache's built-in methods to restrict access in specific
        ways.</para>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authn.basic">
        <title>Setting up HTTP authentication</title>

        <para>The easiest way to authenticate a client is via the
          HTTP Basic authentication mechanism, which simply uses a
          username and password to verify that a user is who she says
          she is.  Apache provides an <command>htpasswd</command>
          utility for managing the list of acceptable usernames and
          passwords.  Let's grant commit access to
          Sally and Harry.  First, we need to add them to the password
          file:</para>

        <screen>
$ ### First time: use -c to create the file
$ ### Use -m to use MD5 encryption of the password, which is more secure
$ htpasswd -cm /etc/svn-auth-file harry
New password: *****
Re-type new password: *****
Adding password for user harry
$ htpasswd -m /etc/svn-auth-file sally
New password: *******
Re-type new password: *******
Adding password for user sally
$
</screen>

        <para>Next, you need to add some more
          <filename>httpd.conf</filename> directives inside your
          <literal>Location</literal> block to tell Apache what to do
          with your new password file.  The
          <literal>AuthType</literal> directive specifies the type of
          authentication system to use.  In this case, we want to
          specify the <literal>Basic</literal> authentication system.
          <literal>AuthName</literal> is an arbitrary name that you
          give for the authentication domain.  Most browsers will
          display this name in the pop-up dialog box when the browser
          is querying the user for her name and password.  Finally,
          use the <literal>AuthUserFile</literal> directive to specify
          the location of the password file you created using
          <command>htpasswd</command>.</para>

        <para>After adding these three directives, your
          <literal>&lt;Location&gt;</literal> block should look
          something like this:</para>

        <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn
  AuthType Basic
  AuthName "Subversion repository"
  AuthUserFile /etc/svn-auth-file
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

        <para>This <literal>&lt;Location&gt;</literal> block is not
          yet complete, and it will not do anything useful.  It's
          merely telling Apache that whenever authorization is
          required, Apache should harvest a username and password from
          the Subversion client.  What's missing here, however, are
          directives that tell Apache <emphasis>which</emphasis> sorts
          of client requests require authorization.  Wherever
          authorization is required, Apache will demand authentication
          as well.  The simplest thing to do is protect all requests.
          Adding <literal>Require valid-user</literal> tells Apache
          that all requests require an authenticated user:</para>

        <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn
  AuthType Basic
  AuthName "Subversion repository"
  AuthUserFile /etc/svn-auth-file
  Require valid-user
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

        <para>Be sure to read the next section (<xref
          linkend="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz"/>) for more detail on the
          <literal>Require</literal> directive and other ways to set
          authorization policies.</para>

        <para>One word of warning: HTTP Basic Auth passwords pass in
          very nearly plain text over the network, and thus are
          extremely insecure.</para>

        <para>Another option is to not use Basic authentication, but to
          use Digest authentication instead.  Digest authentication
          allows the server to verify the client's
          identity <emphasis>without</emphasis> passing the plain-text
          password over the network.  Assuming that the client and
          server both know the user's password, they can verify that
          the password is the same by using it to apply a hashing
          function to a one-time bit of information.  The server sends
          a small random-ish string to the client; the client uses the
          user's password to hash the string; the server then looks to
          see whether the hashed value is what it expected.</para>

        <para>Configuring Apache for Digest authentication is also
          fairly easy, and only a small variation on our prior
          example.  Be sure to consult Apache's documentation for full
          details.</para>

        <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn
  AuthType Digest
  AuthName "Subversion repository"
  AuthDigestDomain /svn/
  AuthUserFile /etc/svn-auth-file
  Require valid-user
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

        <para>If you're looking for maximum security, public key
          cryptography is the best solution.  It may be best to use
          some sort of SSL encryption, so that clients authenticate
          via <literal>https://</literal> instead
          of <literal>http://</literal>; at a bare minimum, you can
          configure Apache to use a self-signed server certificate.
          <footnote>
            <para>While self-signed server certificates are still
              vulnerable to a <quote>man-in-the-middle</quote> attack,
              such an attack is much more difficult for a casual
              observer to pull off, compared to sniffing unprotected
              passwords.</para>
          </footnote>
          Consult Apache's documentation (and OpenSSL documentation)
          about how to do that.</para>

      </sect3>


      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authn.sslcerts">
        <title>SSL certificate management</title>

        <para>Businesses that need to expose their repositories for access
          outside the company firewall should be conscious of the
          possibility that unauthorized parties could be
          <quote>sniffing</quote> their network traffic.  SSL makes
          that kind of unwanted attention less likely to result in
          sensitive data leaks.</para>

        <para>If a Subversion client is compiled to use OpenSSL,
          it gains the ability to speak to an Apache server via
          <literal>https://</literal> URLs.  The Neon library used by
          the Subversion client is not only able to verify server
          certificates, but can also supply client certificates when
          challenged.  When the client and server have exchanged SSL
          certificates and successfully authenticated one another, all
          further communication is encrypted via a session key.</para>

        <para>It's beyond the scope of this book to describe how to
          generate client and server certificates and how to
          configure Apache to use them.  Many other books, including
          Apache's own documentation, describe this task.  But what we
          <emphasis>can</emphasis> cover here is how to manage
          server and client certificates from an ordinary Subversion
          client.</para>

        <para>When speaking to Apache via <literal>https://</literal>,
          a Subversion client can receive two different types of
          information:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>A server certificate</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>A demand for a client certificate</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If the client receives a server certificate, it needs to
          verify that it trusts the certificate: is the server really
          who it claims to be?  The OpenSSL library does this by
          examining the signer of the server certificate, or
          <firstterm>certificate authority</firstterm> (CA).  If
          OpenSSL is unable to automatically trust the CA, or if some
          other problem occurs (such as an expired certificate or
          hostname mismatch), the Subversion command-line client will
          ask you whether you want to trust the server certificate
          anyway:</para>

        <screen>
$ svn list https://host.example.com/repos/project

Error validating server certificate for 'https://host.example.com:443':
 - The certificate is not issued by a trusted authority. Use the
   fingerprint to validate the certificate manually!
Certificate information:
 - Hostname: host.example.com
 - Valid: from Jan 30 19:23:56 2004 GMT until Jan 30 19:23:56 2006 GMT
 - Issuer: CA, example.com, Sometown, California, US
 - Fingerprint: 7d:e1:a9:34:33:39:ba:6a:e9:a5:c4:22:98:7b:76:5c:92:a0:9c:7b

(R)eject, accept (t)emporarily or accept (p)ermanently?
</screen>

        <para>This dialogue should look familiar; it's essentially the
          same question you've probably seen coming from your web
          browser (which is just another HTTP client like Subversion).
          If you choose the <literal>(p)</literal>ermanent option, the server certificate
          will be cached in your private runtime
          <filename>auth/</filename> area in just the same way your
          username and password are cached (see <xref
          linkend="svn.serverconfig.netmodel.credcache"/>).  If cached,
          Subversion will automatically trust this certificate
          in future negotiations.</para>

        <para>Your runtime <filename>servers</filename> file also gives
          you the ability to make your Subversion client automatically
          trust specific CAs, either globally or on a per-host basis.
          Simply set the <literal>ssl-authority-files</literal>
          variable to a semicolon-separated list of PEM-encoded CA
          certificates:</para>

        <screen>
[global]
ssl-authority-files = /path/to/CAcert1.pem;/path/to/CAcert2.pem
</screen>

        <para>Many OpenSSL installations also have a predefined set
          of <quote>default</quote> CAs that are nearly universally
          trusted.  To make the Subversion client automatically trust
          these standard authorities, set the
          <literal>ssl-trust-default-ca</literal> variable to
          <literal>true</literal>.</para>

        <para>When talking to Apache, a Subversion client might also
          receive a challenge for a client certificate.  Apache is
          asking the client to identify itself: is the client really
          who it says it is?  If all goes correctly, the Subversion
          client sends back a private certificate signed by a CA that
          Apache trusts.  A client certificate is usually stored on
          disk in encrypted format, protected by a local password.
          When Subversion receives this challenge, it will ask you for
          a path to the certificate and the password that
          protects it:</para>

        <screen>
$ svn list https://host.example.com/repos/project

Authentication realm: https://host.example.com:443
Client certificate filename: /path/to/my/cert.p12
Passphrase for '/path/to/my/cert.p12':  ********
&hellip;
</screen>

        <para>Notice that the client certificate is a
          <quote>p12</quote> file.  To use a client certificate with
          Subversion, it must be in PKCS#12 format, which is a
          portable standard.  Most web browsers are already able to
          import and export certificates in that format.   Another
          option is to use the OpenSSL command-line tools to convert
          existing certificates into PKCS#12.</para>

        <para>Again, the runtime <filename>servers</filename> file
          allows you to automate this challenge on a per-host basis.
          Either or both pieces of information can be described in
          runtime variables:</para>

        <screen>
[groups]
examplehost = host.example.com

[examplehost]
ssl-client-cert-file = /path/to/my/cert.p12
ssl-client-cert-password = somepassword
</screen>

        <para>Once you've set the
          <literal>ssl-client-cert-file</literal> and
          <literal>ssl-client-cert-password</literal> variables, the
          Subversion client can automatically respond to a client
          certificate challenge without prompting you.
          <footnote>
            <para>More security-conscious folk might not want to store
              the client certificate password in the runtime
              <filename>servers</filename> file.</para>
          </footnote>
        </para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz">
      <title>Authorization Options</title>

      <para>At this point, you've configured authentication, but not
        authorization.  Apache is able to challenge clients and
        confirm identities, but it has not been told how to allow or
        restrict access to the clients bearing those identities.  This
        section describes two strategies for controlling access to
        your repositories.</para>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.blanket">
        <title>Blanket access control</title>

        <para>The simplest form of access control is to authorize
          certain users for either read-only access to a repository or
          read/write access to a repository.</para>

        <para>You can restrict access on all repository operations by
          adding the <literal>Require valid-user</literal> directive
          to your <literal>&lt;Location&gt;</literal> block.  Using
          our previous example, this would mean that only clients that
          claimed to be either <literal>harry</literal> or
          <literal>sally</literal> and that provided the correct
          password for their respective username would be allowed to
          do anything with the Subversion repository:</para>

        <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn

  # how to authenticate a user
  AuthType Basic
  AuthName "Subversion repository"
  AuthUserFile /path/to/users/file

  # only authenticated users may access the repository
  Require valid-user
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

        <para>Sometimes you don't need to run such a tight ship.  For
          example, Subversion's own source code repository at
          <ulink url="http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn"/> allows anyone
          in the world to perform read-only repository tasks (such as
          checking out working copies and browsing the repository with
          a web browser), but restricts all write operations to
          authenticated users.  To do this type of selective
          restriction, you can use the <literal>Limit</literal> and
          <literal>LimitExcept</literal> configuration directives.
          Like the <literal>Location</literal> directive, these blocks
          have starting and ending tags, and you would nest them
          inside your <literal>&lt;Location&gt;</literal>
          block.</para>

        <para>The parameters present on the <literal>Limit</literal>
          and <literal>LimitExcept</literal> directives are HTTP
          request types that are affected by that block.  For example,
          if you wanted to disallow all access to your repository
          except the currently supported read-only operations, you
          would use the <literal>LimitExcept</literal> directive,
          passing the <literal>GET</literal>,
          <literal>PROPFIND</literal>, <literal>OPTIONS</literal>, and
          <literal>REPORT</literal> request type parameters.  Then the
          previously mentioned <literal>Require valid-user</literal>
          directive would be placed inside the
          <literal>&lt;LimitExcept&gt;</literal> block instead of just
          inside the <literal>&lt;Location&gt;</literal> block.</para>

        <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn

  # how to authenticate a user
  AuthType Basic
  AuthName "Subversion repository"
  AuthUserFile /path/to/users/file

  # For any operations other than these, require an authenticated user.
  &lt;LimitExcept GET PROPFIND OPTIONS REPORT&gt;
    Require valid-user
  &lt;/LimitExcept&gt;
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

        <para>These are only a few simple examples.  For more in-depth
          information about Apache access control and the
          <literal>Require</literal> directive, take a look at the
          <literal>Security</literal> section of the Apache
          documentation's tutorials collection at <ulink
           url="http://httpd.apache.org/docs-2.0/misc/tutorials.html"/>.</para>


      </sect3>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.perdir">
        <title>Per-directory access control</title>

        <para>It's possible to set up finer-grained permissions using
          a second Apache httpd module,
          <command>mod_authz_svn</command>.  This module grabs the
          various opaque URLs passing from client to server, asks
          <command>mod_dav_svn</command> to decode them, and then
          possibly vetoes requests based on access policies defined in
          a configuration file.</para>

        <para>If you've built Subversion from source code,
          <command>mod_authz_svn</command> is automatically built
          and installed alongside <command>mod_dav_svn</command>.
          Many binary distributions install it automatically as well.
          To verify that it's installed correctly, make sure it comes
          right after <command>mod_dav_svn</command>'s
          <literal>LoadModule</literal> directive in
          <filename>httpd.conf</filename>:</para>

        <screen>
LoadModule dav_module         modules/mod_dav.so
LoadModule dav_svn_module     modules/mod_dav_svn.so
LoadModule authz_svn_module   modules/mod_authz_svn.so
</screen>

        <para>To activate this module, you need to configure your
          <literal>Location</literal> block to use the
          <literal>AuthzSVNAccessFile</literal> directive, which
          specifies a file containing the permissions policy for paths
          within your repositories.  (In a moment, we'll discuss the
          format of that file.)</para>

        <para>Apache is flexible, so you have the option to configure
          your block in one of three general patterns.  To begin,
          choose one of these basic configuration patterns.  (The
          following examples are very simple; look at Apache's own
          documentation for much more detail on Apache authentication
          and authorization options.)</para>

        <para>The simplest block is to allow open access to everyone.
          In this scenario, Apache never sends authentication
          challenges, so all users are treated as
          <quote>anonymous.</quote> (See
          <xref linkend="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.perdir.ex-1"/>.)</para>

        <example id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.perdir.ex-1">
          <title>A sample configuration for anonymous access</title>
          <programlisting>
&lt;Location /repos&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn

  # our access control policy
  AuthzSVNAccessFile /path/to/access/file
&lt;/Location&gt;
          </programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>On the opposite end of the paranoia scale, you can
          configure your block to demand authentication from everyone.
          All clients must supply credentials to identify themselves.
          Your block unconditionally requires authentication via the
          <literal>Require valid-user</literal> directive, and it
          defines a means to authenticate.  (See
          <xref linkend="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.perdir.ex-2"/>.)</para>

        <example id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.perdir.ex-2">
          <title>A sample configuration for authenticated access</title>
          <programlisting>
&lt;Location /repos&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn

  # our access control policy
  AuthzSVNAccessFile /path/to/access/file

  # only authenticated users may access the repository
  Require valid-user

  # how to authenticate a user
  AuthType Basic
  AuthName "Subversion repository"
  AuthUserFile /path/to/users/file
&lt;/Location&gt;
          </programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>A third very popular pattern is to allow a combination
          of authenticated and anonymous access.  For example, many
          administrators want to allow anonymous users to read certain
          repository directories, but want only authenticated users to
          read (or write) more sensitive areas.  In this setup, all
          users start out accessing the repository anonymously.  If
          your access control policy demands a real username at any
          point, Apache will demand authentication from the client.
          To do this, use both the <literal>Satisfy Any</literal>
          and <literal>Require valid-user</literal> directives
          together.  (See
          <xref linkend="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.perdir.ex-3"/>.)</para>

        <example id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.perdir.ex-3">
          <title>A sample configuration for mixed
            authenticated/anonymous access</title>
          <programlisting>
&lt;Location /repos&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn

  # our access control policy
  AuthzSVNAccessFile /path/to/access/file

  # try anonymous access first, resort to real
  # authentication if necessary.
  Satisfy Any
  Require valid-user

  # how to authenticate a user
  AuthType Basic
  AuthName "Subversion repository"
  AuthUserFile /path/to/users/file
&lt;/Location&gt;
          </programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>Once you've settled on one of these three
          basic <filename>httpd.conf</filename> templates, you need to
          create your file containing access rules for particular
          paths within the repository.  We describe this later in
          this chapter, in
          <xref linkend="svn.serverconfig.pathbasedauthz"/>.</para>

      </sect3>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.pathauthzoff">
        <title>Disabling path-based checks</title>

        <para>The <command>mod_dav_svn</command> module goes through a
          lot of work to make sure that data you've marked
          <quote>unreadable</quote> doesn't get accidentally leaked.
          This means it needs to closely monitor all of the paths
          and file-contents returned by commands such as <command>svn
          checkout</command> and <command>svn update</command>.
          If these commands encounter a path that isn't
          readable according to some authorization policy, the
          path is typically omitted altogether.  In the case of
          history or rename tracing&mdash;for example, running a command such
          as <userinput>svn cat -r OLD foo.c</userinput> on a file that
          was renamed long ago&mdash;the rename tracking will simply
          halt if one of the object's former names is determined to be
          read-restricted.</para>

        <para>All of this path checking can sometimes be quite
          expensive, especially in the case of <command>svn
          log</command>.  When retrieving a list of revisions, the
          server looks at every changed path in each revision and
          checks it for readability.  If an unreadable path is
          discovered, it's omitted from the list of the
          revision's changed paths (normally seen with
          the <option>--verbose</option> option), and the whole log
          message is suppressed.  Needless to say, this can be
          time-consuming on revisions that affect a large number of
          files.  This is the cost of security: even if you haven't
          configured a module such as
          <command>mod_authz_svn</command> at all, the
          <command>mod_dav_svn</command> module is still asking Apache
          <command>httpd</command> to run authorization checks on
          every path.  The <command>mod_dav_svn</command> module has
          no idea what authorization modules have been installed, so
          all it can do is ask Apache to invoke whatever might be
          present.</para>

        <para>On the other hand, there's also an escape hatch of
          sorts, which allows you to trade security features for
          speed.  If you're not enforcing any sort of per-directory
          authorization (i.e., not using
          <command>mod_authz_svn</command> or similar module),
          you can disable all of this path checking.  In your
          <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file, use the
          <literal>SVNPathAuthz</literal> directive as shown in
          <xref linkend="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.pathauthzoff.ex-1"/>.
        </para>

        <example id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.pathauthzoff.ex-1">
          <title>Disabling path checks altogether</title>
          <programlisting>
&lt;Location /repos&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn

  SVNPathAuthz off
&lt;/Location&gt;
          </programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>The <literal>SVNPathAuthz</literal> directive
          is <quote>on</quote> by default.  When
          set to <quote>off,</quote> all path-based authorization
          checking is disabled;
          <command>mod_dav_svn</command> stops invoking authorization
          checks on every path it discovers.</para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.extra">
      <title>Extra Goodies</title>

      <para>We've covered most of the authentication and authorization
        options for Apache and <command>mod_dav_svn</command>.  But
        there are a few other nice features that Apache
        provides.</para>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.extra.browsing">
        <title>Repository browsing</title>

        <para>One of the most useful benefits of an Apache/WebDAV
          configuration for your Subversion repository is that the
          youngest revisions of your versioned files and directories
          are immediately available for viewing via a regular web
          browser.  Since Subversion uses URLs to identify versioned
          resources, those URLs used for HTTP-based repository access
          can be typed directly into a web browser.  Your browser will
          issue an HTTP <literal>GET</literal> request for that URL;
          based on whether that URL represents a versioned directory
          or file, <command>mod_dav_svn</command> will respond with a
          directory listing or with file contents.</para>

        <para>Since the URLs do not contain any information about
          which version of the resource you wish to
          see, <command>mod_dav_svn</command> will always answer with
          the youngest version.  This functionality has the wonderful
          side effect that you can pass around Subversion URLs to your
          peers as references to documents, and those URLs will always
          point at the latest manifestation of that document.  Of
          course, you can even use the URLs as hyperlinks from other
          web sites, too.</para>

        <sidebar>
          <title>Can I View Older Revisions?</title>

          <para>With an ordinary web browser?  In one word: nope.  At
            least, not with <command>mod_dav_svn</command> as your
            only tool.</para>

          <para>Your web browser speaks ordinary HTTP only.  That
            means it knows only how to GET public URLs, which
            represent the latest versions of files and directories.
            According to the WebDAV/DeltaV specification, each server
            defines a private URL syntax for older versions of
            resources, and that syntax is opaque to clients.  To find
            an older version of a file, a client must follow a
            specific procedure to <quote>discover</quote> the proper
            URL; the procedure involves issuing a series of WebDAV
            PROPFIND requests and understanding DeltaV concepts.  This
            is something your web browser simply can't do.</para>

          <para>So, to answer the question, one obvious way to see
            older revisions of files and directories is by passing the
            <option>--revision</option> (<option>-r</option>) argument
            to the <command>svn list</command> and <command>svn
            cat</command> commands.  To browse old revisions with your
            web browser, however, you can use third-party software.  A
            good example of this is ViewVC (<ulink
            url="http://viewvc.tigris.org/"/>).  ViewVC was originally
            written to display CVS repositories through the Web,
            <footnote>
              <para>Back then, it was called ViewCVS.</para>
            </footnote>
            and the latest releases are able to understand Subversion
            repositories as well.</para>
        </sidebar>

        <sect4 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.extra.browsing.mimetype">
          <title>Proper MIME type</title>

          <para>When browsing a Subversion repository, the web browser
            gets a clue about how to render a file's contents by
            looking at the <literal>Content-Type:</literal> header
            returned in Apache's response to the
            HTTP <literal>GET</literal> request.  The value of this
            header is some sort of MIME type.  By default, Apache will
            tell the web browsers that all repository files are of
            the <quote>default</quote> MIME type,
            typically <literal>text/plain</literal>.  This can be
            frustrating, however, if a user wishes repository files to
            render as something more meaningful&mdash;for example,
            it might be nice to have a <filename>foo.html</filename> file
            in the repository actually render as HTML when
            browsing.</para>

          <para>To make this happen, you need only to make sure that
            your files have the
            proper <literal>svn:mime-type</literal> set.  We discuss this 
            in more detail in
            <xref linkend="svn.advanced.props.special.mime-type"/>,
            and you can even configure your client to automatically
            attach proper <literal>svn:mime-type</literal> properties
            to files entering the repository for the first time; see
            <xref linkend="svn.advanced.props.auto"/>.</para>

          <para>So in our example, if one were to set
          the <literal>svn:mime-type</literal> property
          to <literal>text/html</literal> on
          file <filename>foo.html</filename>, Apache would
          properly tell your web browser to render the file as HTML.
          One could also attach proper <literal>image/*</literal>
          MIME-type properties to image files and ultimately get an
          entire web site to be viewable directly from a repository!
          There's generally no problem with this, as long as the web
          site doesn't contain any dynamically generated
          content.</para>

        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.extra.browsing.xslt">
          <title>Customizing the look</title>

          <para>You generally will get more use out of URLs to
            versioned files&mdash;after all, that's where the
            interesting content tends to lie.  But you might have
            occasion to browse a Subversion directory listing, where
            you'll quickly note that the generated HTML used to
            display that listing is very basic, and certainly not
            intended to be aesthetically pleasing (or even
            interesting).  To enable customization of these directory
            displays, Subversion provides an XML index feature.  A
            single <literal>SVNIndexXSLT</literal> directive in your
            repository's <literal>Location</literal> block of
            <filename>httpd.conf</filename> will
            instruct <command>mod_dav_svn</command> to generate XML
            output when displaying a directory listing, and to
            reference the XSLT stylesheet of your choice:</para>

        <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn
  SVNIndexXSLT "/svnindex.xsl"
  &hellip;
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

         <para>Using the <literal>SVNIndexXSLT</literal> directive and
           a creative XSLT stylesheet, you can make your directory
           listings match the color schemes and imagery used in other
           parts of your web site.  Or, if you'd prefer, you can use
           the sample stylesheets provided in the Subversion source
           distribution's <filename>tools/xslt/</filename> directory.
           Keep in mind that the path provided to the
           <literal>SVNIndexXSLT</literal> directory is actually a URL
           path&mdash;browsers need to be able to read your
           stylesheets to make use of them!</para>

         </sect4>

        <sect4 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.extra.browsing.reposlisting">
          <title>Listing repositories</title>

          <para>If you're serving a collection of repositories from a
            single URL via the <literal>SVNParentPath</literal>
            directive, then it's also possible to have Apache display
            all available repositories to a web browser.  Just
            activate the <literal>SVNListParentPath</literal>
            directive:</para>

          <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /var/svn
  SVNListParentPath on
  &hellip;
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

          <para>If a user now points her web browser to the
          URL <literal>http://host.example.com/svn/</literal>, she'll
          see a list of all Subversion repositories sitting
          in <filename>/var/svn</filename>.  Obviously, this can
          be a security problem, so this feature is turned off by
          default.</para>

        </sect4>

      </sect3>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.extra.logging">
        <title>Apache logging</title>

        <para>Because Apache is an HTTP server at heart, it contains
          fantastically flexible logging features.  It's beyond the
          scope of this book to discuss all of the ways logging can be
          configured, but we should point out that even the most
          generic <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file will cause
          Apache to produce two logs:
          <filename>error_log</filename>
          and <filename>access_log</filename>.  These logs may appear
          in different places, but are typically created in the
          logging area of your Apache installation.  (On Unix, they
          often live
          in <filename>/usr/local/apache2/logs/</filename>.)</para>

        <para>The <filename>error_log</filename> describes any internal
          errors that Apache runs into as it works.
          The <filename>access_log</filename> file records every
          incoming HTTP request received by Apache.  This makes it
          easy to see, for example, which IP addresses Subversion
          clients are coming from, how often particular clients use
          the server, which users are authenticating properly, and
          which requests succeed or fail.</para>

        <para>Unfortunately, because HTTP is a stateless protocol,
          even the simplest Subversion client operation generates
          multiple network requests.  It's very difficult to look at
          the <filename>access_log</filename> and deduce what the
          client was doing&mdash;most operations look like a series
          of cryptic <literal>PROPPATCH</literal>, <literal>GET</literal>,
          <literal>PUT</literal>, and <literal>REPORT</literal>
          requests.  To make things worse, many client operations send
          nearly identical series of requests, so it's even harder to
          tell them apart.</para>

        <para><command>mod_dav_svn</command>, however, can come to
          your aid.  By activating an <quote>operational
          logging</quote> feature, you can
          ask <command>mod_dav_svn</command> to create a separate log
          file describing what sort of high-level operations your
          clients are performing.</para>

        <para>To do this, you need to make use of
          Apache's <literal>CustomLog</literal> directive (which is
          explained in more detail in Apache's own documentation).
          Be sure to invoke this
          directive <emphasis>outside</emphasis> your
          Subversion <literal>Location</literal> block:</para>

        <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  &hellip;
&lt;/Location&gt;

CustomLog logs/svn_logfile "%t %u %{SVN-ACTION}e" env=SVN-ACTION
</screen>

        <para>In this example, we're asking Apache to create a special
          logfile, <filename>svn_logfile</filename>, in the standard
          Apache <filename>logs</filename> directory.
          The <literal>%t</literal> and <literal>%u</literal>
          variables are replaced by the time and username of the
          request, respectively.  The really important parts are the
          two instances of <literal>SVN-ACTION</literal>.
          When Apache sees that variable, it substitutes the value of
          the <literal>SVN-ACTION</literal> environment variable,
          which is automatically set by <command>mod_dav_svn</command>
          whenever it detects a high-level client action.</para>

        <para>So, instead of having to interpret a
          traditional <filename>access_log</filename> like
          this:</para>

        <screen>
[26/Jan/2007:22:25:29 -0600] "PROPFIND /svn/calc/!svn/vcc/default HTTP/1.1" 207 398
[26/Jan/2007:22:25:29 -0600] "PROPFIND /svn/calc/!svn/bln/59 HTTP/1.1" 207 449
[26/Jan/2007:22:25:29 -0600] "PROPFIND /svn/calc HTTP/1.1" 207 647
[26/Jan/2007:22:25:29 -0600] "REPORT /svn/calc/!svn/vcc/default HTTP/1.1" 200 607
[26/Jan/2007:22:25:31 -0600] "OPTIONS /svn/calc HTTP/1.1" 200 188
[26/Jan/2007:22:25:31 -0600] "MKACTIVITY /svn/calc/!svn/act/e6035ef7-5df0-4ac0-b811-4be7c823f998 HTTP/1.1" 201 227
&hellip;
</screen>

        <para>you can peruse a much more
          intelligible <filename>svn_logfile</filename> like
          this:</para>

        <screen>
[26/Jan/2007:22:24:20 -0600] - get-dir /tags r1729 props
[26/Jan/2007:22:24:27 -0600] - update /trunk r1729 depth=infinity send-copyfrom-args
[26/Jan/2007:22:25:29 -0600] - status /trunk/foo r1729 depth=infinity
[26/Jan/2007:22:25:31 -0600] sally commit r1730
</screen>

        <para>For an exhaustive list of all actions logged, see <xref
          linkend="svn.ref.mod_dav_svn.conf.logging"/>.</para>

      </sect3>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.extra.writethruproxy">
        <title>Write-through proxying</title>

        <para>One of the nice advantages of using Apache as a
          Subversion server is that it can be set up for simple
          replication.  For example, suppose that your team is
          distributed across four offices around the globe.  The
          Subversion repository can exist only in one of those
          offices, which means the other three offices will not enjoy
          accessing it&mdash;they're likely to experience
          significantly slower traffic and response times when
          updating and committing code.  A powerful solution is to set
          up a system consisting of one <firstterm>master</firstterm>
          Apache server and several <firstterm>slave</firstterm>
          Apache servers.  If you place a slave server in each office,
          users can check out a working copy from whichever slave
          is closest to them.  All read requests go to their local
          slave.  Write requests get automatically routed to the
          single master server.  When the commit completes, the master
          then automatically <quote>pushes</quote> the new revision to
          each slave server using the <command>svnsync</command>
          replication tool.</para>

        <para>This configuration creates a huge perceptual speed
          increase for your users, because Subversion client traffic
          is typically 80&ndash;90% read requests.  And if those
          requests are coming from a <emphasis>local</emphasis>
          server, it's a huge win.</para>

        <para>In this section, we'll walk you through a standard setup
          of this single-master/multiple-slave system.  However, keep
          in mind that your servers must be running at least Apache
          2.2.0 (with <command>mod_proxy</command> loaded) and
          Subversion 1.5 (<command>mod_dav_svn</command>).</para>

        <sect4 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.extra.writethruproxy.configure">
          <title>Configure the servers</title>

          <para>First, configure your master server's
            <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file in the usual way.
            Make the repository available at a certain URI location,
            and configure authentication and authorization however
            you'd like.  After that's done, configure each of your
            <quote>slave</quote> servers in the exact same way, but
            add the special <literal>SVNMasterURI</literal> directive
            to the block:</para>

          <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNPath /var/svn/repos
  SVNMasterURI http://master.example.com/svn
  &hellip;
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

          <para>This new directive tells a slave server to redirect
            all write requests to the master.  (This is done
            automatically via Apache's <command>mod_proxy</command>
            module.)  Ordinary read requests, however, are still
            serviced by the slaves.  Be sure that your master and
            slave servers all have matching authentication and
            authorization configurations;  if they fall out of sync,
            it can lead to big headaches.</para>

          <para>Next, we need to deal with the problem of infinite
            recursion.  With the current configuration, imagine what
            will happen when a Subversion client performs a commit to
            the master server.  After the commit completes, the server
            uses <command>svnsync</command> to replicate the new
            revision to each slave.  But because
            <command>svnsync</command> appears to be just another
            Subversion client performing a commit, the slave will
            immediately attempt to proxy the incoming write request
            back to the master!  Hilarity ensues.</para>

          <para>The solution to this problem is to have the master
            push revisions to a different
            <literal>&lt;Location&gt;</literal> on the slaves.  This
            location is configured to <emphasis>not</emphasis> proxy
            write requests at all, but to accept normal commits from
            (and only from) the master's IP address:</para>

          <screen>
&lt;Location /svn-proxy-sync&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNPath /var/svn/repos
  Order deny,allow
  Deny from all
  # Only let the server's IP address access this Location:
  Allow from 10.20.30.40
  &hellip;
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.extra.writethruproxy.replicate">
          <title>Set up replication</title>

          <para>Now that you've configured
            your <literal>Location</literal> blocks on master and
            slaves, you need to configure the master to replicate to
            the slaves.  This is done the usual way&mdash;
            using <command>svnsync</command>.  If you're not familiar
            with this tool, see
            <xref linkend="svn.reposadmin.maint.replication"/> for
            details.</para>

          <para>First, make sure that each slave repository has a
            <filename>pre-revprop-change</filename> hook script which
            allows remote revision property changes.  (This is
            standard procedure for being on the receiving end of
            <command>svnsync</command>.) Then log into the master
            server and configure each of the slave repository URIs to
            receive data from the master repository on the local
            disk:</para>

          <screen>
$ svnsync init http://slave1.example.com/svn-proxy-sync file://var/svn/repos
Copied properties for revision 0.
$ svnsync init http://slave2.example.com/svn-proxy-sync file://var/svn/repos
Copied properties for revision 0.
$ svnsync init http://slave3.example.com/svn-proxy-sync file://var/svn/repos
Copied properties for revision 0.

# Perform the initial replication

$ svnsync sync http://slave1.example.com/svn-proxy-sync
Transmitting file data ....
Committed revision 1.
Copied properties for revision 1.
Transmitting file data .......
Committed revision 2.
Copied properties for revision 2.
&hellip;

$ svnsync sync http://slave2.example.com/svn-proxy-sync
Transmitting file data ....
Committed revision 1.
Copied properties for revision 1.
Transmitting file data .......
Committed revision 2.
Copied properties for revision 2.
&hellip;

$ svnsync sync http://slave3.example.com/svn-proxy-sync
Transmitting file data ....
Committed revision 1.
Copied properties for revision 1.
Transmitting file data .......
Committed revision 2.
Copied properties for revision 2.
&hellip;
</screen>

          <para>After this is done, we configure the master server's
            <literal>post-commit</literal> hook script to invoke
            <command>svnsync</command> on each slave server:</para>

          <programlisting>
#!/bin/sh
# Post-commit script to replicate newly committed revision to slaves

svnsync sync http://slave1.example.com/svn-proxy-sync &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1
svnsync sync http://slave2.example.com/svn-proxy-sync &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1
svnsync sync http://slave3.example.com/svn-proxy-sync &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1
</programlisting>

          <para>The extra bits on the end of each line aren't
            necessary, but they're a sneaky way to allow the sync
            commands to run in the background so that the Subversion
            client isn't left waiting forever for the commit to
            finish.  In addition to this
            <literal>post-commit</literal> hook, you'll need a
            <literal>post-revprop-change</literal> hook as well so
            that when a user, say, modifies a log message, the slave
            servers get that change also:</para>

          <programlisting>
#!/bin/sh
# Post-revprop-change script to replicate revprop-changes to slaves

REV=${2}
svnsync copy-revprops http://slave1.example.com/svn-proxy-sync ${REV} &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1
svnsync copy-revprops http://slave2.example.com/svn-proxy-sync ${REV} &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1
svnsync copy-revprops http://slave3.example.com/svn-proxy-sync ${REV} &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1
</programlisting>

          <para>The only thing we've left out here is what to do about
            locks.  Because locks are strictly enforced by the master
            server (the only place where commits happen), we don't
            technically need to do anything.  Many teams don't use
            Subversion's locking features at all, so it may be a
            nonissue for you.  However, if lock changes aren't
            replicated from master to slaves, it means that clients
            won't be able to query the status of locks
            (e.g., <userinput>svn status -u</userinput> will show no
            information about repository locks).  If this bothers you,
            you can write <literal>post-lock</literal> and
            <literal>post-unlock</literal> hook scripts that run
            <command>svn lock</command> and <command>svn
            unlock</command> on each slave machine, presumably through
            a remote shell method such as SSH.  That's left as an
            exercise for the reader!</para>

        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.extra.writethruproxy.caveats">
          <title>Caveats</title>

          <para>Your master/slave replication system should now be
            ready to use.  A couple of words of warning are in order,
            however.  Remember that this replication isn't entirely
            robust in the face of computer or network crashes.  For
            example, if one of the automated
            <command>svnsync</command> commands fails to complete for
            some reason, the slaves will begin to fall behind.  For
            example, your remote users will see that they've committed
            revision 100, but then when they run <command>svn
            update</command>, their local server will tell them that
            revision 100 doesn't yet exist!  Of course, the problem
            will be automatically fixed the next time another commit
            happens and the subsequent <command>svnsync</command> is
            successful&mdash;the sync will replicate all waiting
            revisions.  But still, you may want to set up some sort of
            out-of-band monitoring to notice synchronization failures
            and force <command>svnsync</command> to run when things go
            wrong.</para>

          <sidebar>
            <title>Can We Set Up Replication with svnserve?</title>

            <para>If you're using <command>svnserve</command> instead
              of Apache as your server, you can certainly configure
              your repository's hook scripts to invoke
              <command>svnsync</command> as we've shown here, thereby
              causing automatic replication from master to slaves.
              Unfortunately, at the time of this writing there is no way to
              make slave <command>svnserve</command> servers
              automatically proxy write requests back to the master
              server.  This means your users would only be able to
              check out read-only working copies from the slave
              servers.  You'd have to configure your slave servers to
              disallow write access completely.  This might be useful
              for creating read-only <quote>mirrors</quote> of popular
              open source projects, but it's not a transparent
              proxying system.</para> </sidebar>

        </sect4>

        </sect3>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
      <sect3 id="svn.serverconfig.httpd.extra.other">
        <title>Other Apache features</title>

        <para>Several of the features already provided by Apache in
          its role as a robust web server can be leveraged for
          increased functionality or security in Subversion as well.
          The Subversion client is able to use SSL (the Secure Sockets
          Layer, discussed earlier).  If your Subversion client is
          built to support SSL, it can access your Apache server
          using <literal>https://</literal> and enjoy a high-quality
          encrypted network session.</para>

        <para>Equally useful are other features of the Apache and
          Subversion relationship, such as the ability to specify a
          custom port (instead of the default HTTP port 80) or a
          virtual domain name by which the Subversion repository
          should be accessed, or the ability to access the repository
          through an HTTP proxy.</para>

        <para>Finally, because <command>mod_dav_svn</command> is
          speaking a subset of the WebDAV/DeltaV protocol, it's
          possible to access the repository via third-party DAV
          clients.  Most modern operating systems (Win32, OS X, and
          Linux) have the built-in ability to mount a DAV server as a
          standard network <quote>shared folder.</quote> This is a
          complicated topic, but also wondrous when implemented.  For
          details, read <xref linkend="svn.webdav"/>.</para>

        <para>Note that there are a number of other small tweaks one can
          make to <command>mod_dav_svn</command> that are too obscure
          to mention in this chapter.  For a complete list of
          all <filename>httpd.conf</filename> directives
          that <command>mod_dav_svn</command> responds to, see
          <xref linkend="svn.ref.mod_dav_svn.conf.directives"/>.</para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.serverconfig.pathbasedauthz">

    <title>Path-Based Authorization</title>

    <para>Both Apache and <command>svnserve</command> are capable of
      granting (or denying) permissions to users.  Typically this is
      done over the entire repository: a user can read the repository
      (or not), and she can write to the repository (or not).  It's
      also possible, however, to define finer-grained access rules.
      One set of users may have permission to write to a certain
      directory in the repository, but not others; another directory
      might not even be readable by all but a few special
      people.</para>

    <para>Both servers use a common file format to describe these
      path-based access rules.  In the case of Apache, one needs to
      load the <command>mod_authz_svn</command> module and then add
      the <literal>AuthzSVNAccessFile</literal> directive (within
      the <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file) pointing to your own
      rules file.  (For a full explanation, see
      <xref linkend="svn.serverconfig.httpd.authz.perdir"/>.)  If
      you're using <command>svnserve</command>, you need to make
      the <literal>authz-db</literal> variable
      (within <filename>svnserve.conf</filename>) point to your
      rules file.</para>

    <sidebar>
      <title>Do You Really Need Path-Based Access Control?</title>

      <para>A lot of administrators setting up Subversion for the
        first time tend to jump into path-based access control without
        giving it a lot of thought.  The administrator usually knows
        which teams of people are working on which projects, so it's
        easy to jump in and grant certain teams access to certain
        directories and not others.  It seems like a natural thing,
        and it appeases the administrator's desire to maintain tight
        control of the repository.</para>

      <para>Note, though, that there are often invisible (and
        visible!) costs associated with this feature.  In the visible
        category, the server needs to do a lot more work to ensure
        that the user has the right to read or write each specific
        path; in certain situations, there's very noticeable
        performance loss.  In the invisible category, consider the
        culture you're creating.  Most of the time, while certain
        users <emphasis>shouldn't</emphasis> be committing changes to
        certain parts of the repository, that social contract doesn't
        need to be technologically enforced.  Teams can sometimes
        spontaneously collaborate with each other; someone may want to
        help someone else out by committing to an area she doesn't
        normally work on.  By preventing this sort of thing at the
        server level, you're setting up barriers to unexpected
        collaboration.  You're also creating a bunch of rules that
        need to be maintained as projects develop, new users are
        added, and so on.  It's a bunch of extra work to
        maintain.</para>

        <para>Remember that this is a version control system!  Even if
        somebody accidentally commits a change to something she
        shouldn't, it's easy to undo the change.  And if a user
        commits to the wrong place with deliberate malice, it's a
        social problem anyway, and that the problem needs to be dealt
        with outside Subversion.</para>

      <para>So, before you begin restricting users' access rights, ask
        yourself whether there's a real, honest need for this, or whether it's
        just something that <quote>sounds good</quote> to an
        administrator.  Decide whether it's worth sacrificing some
        server speed, and remember that there's very little risk
        involved; it's bad to become dependent on technology as a
        crutch for social problems.
        <footnote>
          <para>A common theme in this book!</para>
        </footnote>
      </para>

      <para>As an example to ponder, consider that the Subversion
        project itself has always had a notion of who is allowed to
        commit where, but it's always been enforced socially.  This is
        a good model of community trust, especially for open source
        projects.  Of course, sometimes there <emphasis>are</emphasis>
        truly legitimate needs for path-based access control; within
        corporations, for example, certain types of data really can be
        sensitive, and access needs to be genuinely restricted to
        small groups of people.</para>

    </sidebar>

    <para>Once your server knows where to find your rules file, it's
      time to define the rules.</para>

    <para>The syntax of the file is the same familiar one used
      by <filename>svnserve.conf</filename> and the runtime
      configuration files.  Lines that start with a hash
      (<literal>#</literal>) are ignored.  In its simplest form, each
      section names a repository and path within it, as well as the
      authenticated usernames are the option names within each
      section.  The value of each option describes the user's level of
      access to the repository path: either
      <literal>r</literal> (read-only) or <literal>rw</literal>
      (read/write).  If the user is not mentioned at all, no access is
      allowed.</para>

    <para>To be more specific: the value of the section names is
      either of the form <literal>[repos-name:path]</literal> or of the
      form <literal>[path]</literal>.  If you're using the
      <literal>SVNParentPath</literal> directive, it's important
      to specify the repository names in your sections.  If you omit
      them, a section such as
      <literal>[/some/dir]</literal> will match the path
      <filename>/some/dir</filename> in <emphasis>every</emphasis>
      repository.  If you're using the <literal>SVNPath</literal>
      directive, however, it's fine to only define paths in your
      sections&mdash;after all, there's only one repository.</para>

    <screen>
[calc:/branches/calc/bug-142]
harry = rw
sally = r
</screen>

    <para>In this first example, the user <literal>harry</literal> has
      full read and write access on the
      <filename>/branches/calc/bug-142</filename> directory in the
      <literal>calc</literal> repository, but the user
      <literal>sally</literal> has read-only access.  Any other users
      are blocked from accessing this directory.</para>

    <para>Of course, permissions are inherited from parent to child
      directory.  That means we can specify a subdirectory with a
      different access policy for Sally:</para>

    <screen>
[calc:/branches/calc/bug-142]
harry = rw
sally = r

# give sally write access only to the 'testing' subdir
[calc:/branches/calc/bug-142/testing]
sally = rw
</screen>

    <para>Now Sally can write to the <filename>testing</filename>
      subdirectory of the branch, but can still only read other parts.
      Harry, meanwhile, continues to have complete read/write access
      to the whole branch.</para>

    <para>It's also possible to explicitly deny permission to someone
      via inheritance rules, by setting the username variable to
      nothing:</para>

    <screen>
[calc:/branches/calc/bug-142]
harry = rw
sally = r

[calc:/branches/calc/bug-142/secret]
harry =
</screen>

    <para>In this example, Harry has read/write access to the
      entire <filename>bug-142</filename> tree, but has absolutely no
      access at all to the <filename>secret</filename> subdirectory
      within it.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>The thing to remember is that the most specific path
        always matches first.  The server tries to match the path
        itself, and then the parent of the path, then the parent of
        that, and so on.  The net effect is that mentioning a specific
        path in the access file will always override any permissions
        inherited from parent directories.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>By default, nobody has any access to the repository at all.
      That means that if you're starting with an empty file, you'll
      probably want to give at least read permission to all users at
      the root of the repository.  You can do this by using the
      asterisk variable (<literal>*</literal>), which means <quote>all
      users</quote>:</para>

    <screen>
[/]
* = r
</screen>

    <para>This is a common setup; notice that no repository
      name is mentioned in the section name.  This makes all repositories
      world-readable to all users. Once all users have read access to
      the repositories, you can give explicit
      <literal>rw</literal> permission to certain users on specific
      subdirectories within specific repositories.</para>

    <para>The asterisk variable (<literal>*</literal>) is also worth
      special mention because it's the
      <emphasis>only</emphasis> pattern that matches an anonymous
      user.  If you've configured your server block to allow a mixture
      of anonymous and authenticated access, all users start out
      accessing anonymously.  The server looks for a
      <literal>*</literal> value defined for the path being accessed;
      if it can't find one, it demands real authentication from
      the client.</para>

    <para>The access file also allows you to define whole groups of
      users, much like the Unix <filename>/etc/group</filename>
      file:</para>

    <screen>
[groups]
calc-developers = harry, sally, joe
paint-developers = frank, sally, jane
everyone = harry, sally, joe, frank, sally, jane
</screen>

    <para>Groups can be granted access control just like users.
      Distinguish them with an <quote>at</quote>
      (<literal>@</literal>) prefix:</para>

    <screen>
[calc:/projects/calc]
@calc-developers = rw

[paint:/projects/paint]
jane = r
@paint-developers = rw
</screen>

    <para>Another important fact is that
    the <emphasis>first</emphasis> matching rule is the one which gets
    applied to a user.  In the prior example, even though Jane is a
    member of the <literal>paint-developers</literal> group (which has
    read/write access), the <literal>jane = r</literal> rule will be
    discovered and matched before the group rule, thus denying Jane
    write access.</para>

    <para>Groups can also be defined to contain other groups:</para>

    <screen>
[groups]
calc-developers = harry, sally, joe
paint-developers = frank, sally, jane
everyone = @calc-developers, @paint-developers
</screen>

    <para>Subversion 1.5 brings another useful feature to the access
      file syntax:  username aliases.  Some authentication systems
      expect and carry relatively short usernames of the sorts we've
      been describing here&mdash;<literal>harry</literal>,
      <literal>sally</literal>, <literal>joe</literal>, and so on.  But
      other authentication systems&mdash;such as those which use LDAP
      stores or SSL client certificates&mdash;may carry much more
      complex usernames.  For example, Harry's username in an
      LDAP-protected system might be <literal>CN=Harold
      Hacker,OU=Engineers,DC=red-bean,DC=com</literal>.  With
      usernames like that, the access file can become quite bloated
      with long or obscure usernames that are easy to mistype.
      Fortunately, username aliases allow you to have to type the
      correct complex username only once, in a statement which assigns to
      it a more easily digestable alias.</para>

    <screen>
[aliases]
harry = CN=Harold Hacker,OU=Engineers,DC=red-bean,DC=com
sally = CN=Sally Swatterbug,OU=Engineers,DC=red-bean,DC=com
joe = CN=Gerald I. Joseph,OU=Engineers,DC=red-bean,DC=com
&hellip;
</screen>

    <para>Once you've defined a set of aliases, you can refer to the
      users elsewhere in the access file via their aliases in all the
      same places you could have instead used their actual usernames.
      Simply prepend an ampersand to the alias to distinguish it from
      a regular username:</para>

    <screen>
[groups]
calc-developers = &amp;harry, &amp;sally, &amp;joe
paint-developers = &amp;frank, &amp;sally, &amp;jane
everyone = @calc-developers, @paint-developers
</screen>

    <para>You might also choose to use aliases if your users'
      usernames change frequently.  Doing so allows you to need to
      update only the aliases table when these username changes occur,
      instead of doing global-search-and-replace operations on the
      whole access file.</para>

  <!-- TODO(sussman): Once serf becomes officially support, this
       sidebar will need to be revisited. -->

  <sidebar>
    <title>Partial Readability and Checkouts</title>

    <para>If you're using Apache as your Subversion server and have
      made certain subdirectories of your repository unreadable to
      certain users, you need to be aware of a possible
      nonoptimal behavior with <command>svn checkout</command>.</para>

    <para>When the client requests a checkout or update over HTTP, it
      makes a single server request and receives a single (often
      large) server response.  When the server receives the request,
      that is the <emphasis>only</emphasis> opportunity Apache has to
      demand user authentication.  This has some odd side effects.
      For example, if a certain subdirectory of the repository is
      readable only by user Sally, and user Harry checks out a parent
      directory, his client will respond to the initial authentication
      challenge as Harry.  As the server generates the large response,
      there's no way it can resend an authentication challenge when
      it reaches the special subdirectory; thus the subdirectory is
      skipped altogether, rather than asking the user to
      reauthenticate as Sally at the right moment.  In a similar way,
      if the root of the repository is anonymously world-readable,
      the entire checkout will be done without
      authentication&mdash;again, skipping the unreadable directory,
      rather than asking for authentication partway through.</para>
  </sidebar>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.serverconfig.multimethod">

    <title>Supporting Multiple Repository Access Methods</title>

    <para>You've seen how a repository can be accessed in many
      different ways.  But is it possible&mdash;or safe&mdash;for your
      repository to be accessed by multiple methods simultaneously?
      The answer is yes, provided you use a bit of foresight.</para>

    <para>At any given time, these processes may require read and
      write access to your repository:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Regular system users using a Subversion client (as
          themselves) to access the repository directly via
          <literal>file://</literal> URLs</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Regular system users connecting to SSH-spawned private
          <command>svnserve</command> processes (running as
          themselves), which access the repository</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>An <command>svnserve</command> process&mdash;either a
          daemon or one launched by
          <command>inetd</command>&mdash;running as a particular fixed
          user</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>An Apache <command>httpd</command> process, running as a
          particular fixed user</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The most common problem administrators run into is
      repository ownership and permissions.  Does every process (or
      user) in the preceding list have the rights to read and write the
      repository's underlying data files?  Assuming you have a
      Unix-like operating system, a straightforward approach might be
      to place every potential repository user into a
      new <literal>svn</literal> group, and make the repository wholly
      owned by that group.  But even that's not enough, because a
      process may write to the database files using an unfriendly
      umask&mdash;one that prevents access by other users.</para>

    <para>So the next step beyond setting up a common group for
      repository users is to force every repository-accessing process
      to use a sane umask.  For users accessing the repository
      directly, you can make the <command>svn</command> program into a
      wrapper script that first runs <userinput>umask 002</userinput> and
      then runs the real <command>svn</command> client program.  You
      can write a similar wrapper script for the
      <command>svnserve</command> program, and add a <userinput>umask
      002</userinput> command to Apache's own startup script,
      <filename>apachectl</filename>.  For example:</para>

    <screen>
$ cat /usr/bin/svn

#!/bin/sh

umask 002
/usr/bin/svn-real "$@"

</screen>

    <para>Another common problem is often encountered on Unix-like
      systems.  If your repository is backed by Berkeley DB, for
      example, it occasionally creates new log files to journal its
      actions.  Even if the Berkeley DB repository is wholly owned by
      the <command>svn</command> group, these newly created log files
      won't necessarily be owned by that same group, which then
      creates more permissions problems for your users.  A good
      workaround is to set the group SUID bit on the
      repository's <filename>db</filename> directory. This causes all
      newly created log files to have the same group owner as the
      parent directory.</para>

    <para>Once you've jumped through these hoops, your repository
      should be accessible by all the necessary processes.  It may
      seem a bit messy and complicated, but the problems of having
      multiple users sharing write access to common files are classic
      ones that are not often elegantly solved.</para>

    <para>Fortunately, most repository administrators will never
      <emphasis>need</emphasis> to have such a complex configuration.
      Users who wish to access repositories that live on the same
      machine are not limited to using <literal>file://</literal>
      access URLs&mdash;they can typically contact the Apache HTTP
      server or <command>svnserve</command> using
      <literal>localhost</literal> for the server name in their
      <literal>http://</literal> or <literal>svn://</literal> URL.
      And maintaining multiple server processes for your Subversion
      repositories is likely to be more of a headache than necessary.
      We recommend that you choose a single server that best meets your
      needs and stick with it!</para>

    <sidebar>
      <title>The svn+ssh:// Server Checklist</title>

      <para>It can be quite tricky to get a bunch of users with
        existing SSH accounts to share a repository without
        permissions problems.  If you're confused about all the things
        that you (as an administrator) need to do on a Unix-like
        system, here's a quick checklist that resummarizes some of the
        topics discussed in this section:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>All of your SSH users need to be able to read and
            write to the repository, so put all the SSH users into a
            single group.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Make the repository wholly owned by that group.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Set the group permissions to
            read/write.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Your users need to use a sane umask when accessing the
            repository, so make sure <command>svnserve</command>
            (<filename>/usr/bin/svnserve</filename>, or wherever it
            lives in <literal>$PATH</literal>) is actually a wrapper
            script that runs <userinput>umask 002</userinput> and
            executes the real <command>svnserve</command>
            binary.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>Take similar measures when using
            <command>svnlook</command> and
            <command>svnadmin</command>.  Either run them with a sane
            umask or wrap them as just described.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </sidebar>

  </sect1>




</chapter>

<!--
local variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
