<appendix id="svn.intro">

  <title>Subversion Quick-Start Guide</title>


  <para>If you're eager to get Subversion up and running (and you
    enjoy learning by experimentation), this appendix will show you how
    to create a repository, import code, and then check it back out
    again as a working copy.  Along the way, we give links to the
    relevant chapters of this book.</para>

  <warning>
  <para>If you're new to the entire concept of version control or to
    the <quote>copy-modify-merge</quote> model used by both CVS and
    Subversion, you should read <xref linkend="svn.basic"/>
    before going any further.</para>
  </warning>


  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.intro.install">

    <title>Installing Subversion</title>

    <para>Subversion is built on a portability layer called
      APR&mdash;the Apache Portable Runtime library.  The APR library
      provides all the interfaces that Subversion needs to function on
      different operating systems: disk access, network access, memory
      management, and so on.  While Subversion is able to use Apache
      as one of its network server programs, its dependence on APR
      <emphasis>does not</emphasis> mean that Apache is a required
      component.  APR is a standalone library usable by any
      application.  It does mean, however, that like Apache,
      Subversion clients and servers run on any operating system that
      the Apache <command>httpd</command> server runs on: Windows,
      Linux, all flavors of BSD, Mac OS X, NetWare, and others.</para>

    <para>The easiest way to get Subversion is to download a binary
      package built for your operating system.  Subversion's web site
      (<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org"/>) often has these
      packages available for download, posted by volunteers.  The site
      usually contains graphical installer packages for users of
      Microsoft operating systems.  If you run a Unix-like operating
      system, you can use your system's native package distribution
      system (RPMs, DEBs, the ports tree, etc.) to get
      Subversion.</para>

    <para>Alternatively, you can build Subversion directly from source
      code, though it's not always an easy task. (If you're not
      experienced at building open source software packages, you're
      probably better off downloading a binary distribution instead!)
      From the Subversion web site, download the latest source code
      release.  After unpacking it, follow the instructions in
      the <filename>INSTALL</filename> file to build it.  Note that a
      released source package may not contain everything you need to
      build a command-line client capable of talking to a remote
      repository.  Starting with Subversion 1.4 and later, the
      libraries Subversion depends on (apr, apr-util, and neon) are
      distributed in a separate source package suffixed
      with <filename>-deps</filename>.  These libraries are now common
      enough that they may already be installed on your system.  If
      not, you'll need to unpack the dependency package into the same
      directory where you unpacked the main Subversion source.
      Regardless, it's possible that you may want to fetch other
      optional dependencies such as Berkeley DB and possibly Apache
      <command>httpd</command>.  If you want to do a complete build,
      make sure you have all of the packages documented in
      the <filename>INSTALL</filename> file.</para>

    <para>If you're one of those folks that likes to use bleeding-edge
      software, you can also get the Subversion source code from the
      Subversion repository in which it lives.  Obviously, you'll need
      to already have a Subversion client on hand to do this.  But
      once you do, you can check out a working copy of the Subversion source
      repository from <ulink url="http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn/trunk/"/>:
      <footnote>
        <para>Note that the URL checked out in the example ends not
          with <literal>svn</literal>, but with a subdirectory thereof
          called <literal>trunk</literal>.  See our discussion of
          Subversion's branching and tagging model for the reasoning
          behind this.</para>
      </footnote>
    </para>

    <screen>
$ svn checkout http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn/trunk subversion
A    subversion/HACKING
A    subversion/INSTALL
A    subversion/README
A    subversion/autogen.sh
A    subversion/build.conf
&hellip;
</screen>

    <para>The preceding command will create a working copy of the
      latest (unreleased) Subversion source code into a subdirectory
      named <filename>subversion</filename> in your current working
      directory.  You can adjust that last argument as you see fit.
      Regardless of what you call the new working copy directory,
      though, after this operation completes, you will now have the
      Subversion source code.  Of course, you will still need to fetch
      a few helper libraries (apr, apr-util, etc.)&mdash;see the
      <filename>INSTALL</filename> file in the top level of the
      working copy for details.</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.intro.quickstart">

    <title>High-Speed Tutorial</title>

    <blockquote>
      <para><quote>Please make sure your seat backs are in their full,
        upright position and that your tray tables are stored.  Flight
        attendants, prepare for take-off&hellip;.</quote></para>
        </blockquote>

    <para>What follows is a quick tutorial that walks you through some
      basic Subversion configuration and operation.  When you finish
      it, you should have a general understanding of Subversion's
      typical usage.</para>

    <note>
      <para>The examples used in this appendix assume that you have
        <command>svn</command>, the Subversion command-line client,
        and <command>svnadmin</command>, the administrative tool,
        ready to go on a Unix-like operating system.  (This tutorial
        also works at the Windows command-line prompt, assuming you
        make some obvious tweaks.)  We also assume you are using
        Subversion 1.2 or later (run <userinput>svn --version</userinput>
        to check.)</para>
    </note>

    <para>Subversion stores all versioned data in a central
      repository.  To begin, create a new repository:</para>

    <screen>
$ svnadmin create /var/svn/repos
$ ls /var/svn/repos
conf/  dav/  db/  format  hooks/  locks/  README.txt
</screen>

    <para>This command creates a new directory,
      <filename>/var/svn/repos</filename>, which contains a Subversion
      repository.  This new directory contains (among other things) a
      collection of database files.  You won't see your versioned
      files if you peek inside.  For more information about repository
      creation and maintenance, see <xref
      linkend="svn.reposadmin"/>.</para>

    <para>Subversion has no concept of a <quote>project.</quote> The
      repository is just a virtual versioned filesystem, a large tree
      that can hold anything you wish.  Some administrators prefer to
      store only one project in a repository, and others prefer to
      store multiple projects in a repository by placing them into
      separate directories.  We discuss the merits of each approach
      in <xref linkend="svn.reposadmin.projects.chooselayout"/>.
      Either way, the repository manages only files and directories,
      so it's up to humans to interpret particular directories as
      <quote>projects.</quote>  So while you might see references to
      projects throughout this book, keep in mind that we're only ever
      talking about some directory (or collection of directories) in
      the repository.</para>

    <para>In this example, we assume you already have some sort
      of project (a collection of files and directories) that you wish
      to import into your newly created Subversion repository.  Begin
      by organizing your data into a single directory called
      <filename>myproject</filename> (or whatever you wish).  For
      reasons explained in <xref linkend="svn.branchmerge"/>, your
      project's tree structure should contain three top-level
      directories named <filename>branches</filename>,
      <filename>tags</filename>, and <filename>trunk</filename>.  The
      <filename>trunk</filename> directory should contain all of your
      data, and the <filename>branches</filename> and
      <filename>tags</filename> directories should be empty:</para>

    <screen>
/tmp/myproject/branches/
/tmp/myproject/tags/
/tmp/myproject/trunk/
                     foo.c
                     bar.c
                     Makefile
                     &hellip;
</screen>

    <para>The <filename>branches</filename>, <filename>tags</filename>,
      and <filename>trunk</filename> subdirectories aren't actually
      required by Subversion.  They're merely a popular convention
      that you'll most likely want to use later on.</para>

    <para>Once you have your tree of data ready to go, import it into
      the repository with the <command>svn import</command> command
      (see <xref linkend="svn.tour.importing"/>):</para>

    <screen>
$ svn import /tmp/myproject file:///var/svn/repos/myproject -m "initial import"
Adding         /tmp/myproject/branches
Adding         /tmp/myproject/tags
Adding         /tmp/myproject/trunk
Adding         /tmp/myproject/trunk/foo.c
Adding         /tmp/myproject/trunk/bar.c
Adding         /tmp/myproject/trunk/Makefile
&hellip;
Committed revision 1.
$ 
</screen>

    <para>Now the repository contains this tree of data.  As mentioned
      earlier, you won't see your files by directly peeking into the
      repository;  they're all stored within a database.  But the
      repository's imaginary filesystem now contains a top-level
      directory named <filename>myproject</filename>, which in turn
      contains your data.</para>

    <para>Note that the original <filename>/tmp/myproject</filename>
      directory is unchanged; Subversion is unaware of it.  (In fact,
      you can even delete that directory if you wish.)  To
      start manipulating repository data, you need to create a new
      <quote>working copy</quote> of the data, a sort of private
      workspace.  Ask Subversion to <quote>check out</quote> a working
      copy of the <filename>myproject/trunk</filename> directory in
      the repository:</para>

    <screen>
$ svn checkout file:///var/svn/repos/myproject/trunk myproject
A  myproject/foo.c
A  myproject/bar.c
A  myproject/Makefile
&hellip;
Checked out revision 1.
</screen>

    <para>Now you have a personal copy of part of the repository in a
      new directory named <filename>myproject</filename>.  You can edit
      the files in your working copy and then commit those changes
      back into the repository.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enter your working copy and edit a file's
          contents.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Run <userinput>svn diff</userinput> to see unified diff
          output of your changes.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Run <userinput>svn commit</userinput> to commit the new
          version of your file to the repository.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Run <userinput>svn update</userinput> to bring your working
          copy <quote>up to date</quote> with the repository.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>For a full tour of all the things you can do with your
      working copy, read <xref linkend="svn.tour"/>.</para>

    <para>At this point, you have the option of making your repository
      available to others over a network.  See <xref
      linkend="svn.serverconfig"/> to learn about the different sorts of
      server processes available and how to configure them.</para>

    <!-- ### TODO: Let's make this into a full tutorial, rather than
             simply referring off to other sections. ### -->

  </sect1>


</appendix>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "appendix")
end:
-->
