<chapter id="svn.developer">
  <title>Embedding Subversion</title>
  
  <para>Subversion has a modular design: it's implemented as a
    collection of libraries written in C.  Each library has a
    well-defined purpose and application programming interface (API),
    and that interface is available not only for Subversion itself to
    use, but for any software that wishes to embed or otherwise
    programmatically control Subversion.  Additionally, Subversion's
    API is available not only to other C programs, but also to
    programs written in higher-level languages such as Python, Perl,
    Java, and Ruby.</para>

  <para>This chapter is for those who wish to interact with Subversion
    through its public API or its various language bindings.  If you
    wish to write robust wrapper scripts around Subversion
    functionality to simplify your own life, are trying to develop
    more complex integrations between Subversion and other pieces of
    software, or just have an interest in Subversion's various library
    modules and what they offer, this chapter is for you.  If,
    however, you don't foresee yourself participating with Subversion
    at such a level, feel free to skip this chapter with the
    confidence that your experience as a Subversion user will not be
    affected.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.developer.layerlib">
    <title>Layered Library Design</title>

    <para>Each of Subversion's core libraries can be said to exist in
      one of three main layers&mdash;the Repository layer, the
      Repository Access (RA) layer, or the Client layer (see <xref
      linkend="svn.intro.architecture.dia-1" /> in the Preface).  We will examine
      these layers shortly, but first, let's briefly summarize
      Subversion's various libraries.  For the sake of consistency, we
      will refer to the libraries by their extensionless Unix library
      names (<filename>libsvn_fs</filename>, <filename>libsvn_wc</filename>,
      <filename>mod_dav_svn</filename>, etc.).</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_client</term> 
        <listitem><para>Primary interface for client
          programs</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_delta</term>
        <listitem><para>Tree and byte-stream differencing
          routines</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_diff</term>
        <listitem><para>Contextual differencing and merging
          routines</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_fs</term>
        <listitem><para>Filesystem commons and module
          loader</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_fs_base</term>
        <listitem><para>The Berkeley DB filesystem
          backend</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_fs_fs</term>
        <listitem><para>The native filesystem (FSFS)
          backend</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_ra</term>
        <listitem><para>Repository Access commons and module
          loader</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_ra_local</term>
        <listitem><para>The local Repository Access
          module</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_ra_neon</term>
        <listitem><para>The WebDAV Repository Access
          module</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_ra_serf</term>
        <listitem><para>Another (experimental) WebDAV Repository
          Access module</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_ra_svn</term>
        <listitem><para>The custom protocol Repository Access
          module</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_repos</term>
        <listitem><para>Repository interface</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_subr</term>
        <listitem><para>Miscellaneous helpful
          subroutines</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>libsvn_wc</term>
        <listitem><para>The working copy management
          library</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>mod_authz_svn</term>
        <listitem><para>Apache authorization module for Subversion
          repositories access via WebDAV</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>mod_dav_svn</term>
        <listitem><para>Apache module for mapping WebDAV operations to
          Subversion ones</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>The fact that the word <quote>miscellaneous</quote>
      appears only once in the previous list is a good sign.  The
      Subversion development team is serious about making sure that
      functionality lives in the right layer and libraries.  Perhaps
      the greatest advantage of the modular design is its lack of
      complexity from a developer's point of view.  As a developer,
      you can quickly formulate that kind of <quote>big
      picture</quote> that allows you to pinpoint the location of
      certain pieces of functionality with relative ease.</para>

    <para>Another benefit of modularity is the ability to replace a
      given module with a whole new library that implements the same
      API without affecting the rest of the code base.  In some sense,
      this happens within Subversion already.  The
      <filename>libsvn_ra_local</filename>,
      <filename>libsvn_ra_neon</filename>,
      <filename>libsvn_ra_serf</filename>, and
      <filename>libsvn_ra_svn</filename> libraries each implement the
      same interface, all working as plug-ins to
      <filename>libsvn_ra</filename>.  And all four communicate with
      the Repository layer&mdash;<filename>libsvn_ra_local</filename> connects to the
      repository directly; the other three do so over a network.  The
      <filename>libsvn_fs_base</filename> and
      <filename>libsvn_fs_fs</filename> libraries are another pair of
      libraries that implement the same functionality in different
      ways&mdash;both are plug-ins to the common
      <filename>libsvn_fs</filename> library.</para>

    <para>The client itself also highlights the benefits of modularity
      in the Subversion design.  Subversion's
      <filename>libsvn_client</filename> library is a one-stop shop
      for most of the functionality necessary for designing a working
      Subversion client (see <xref
      linkend="svn.developer.layerlib.client"/>).  So while the
      Subversion distribution provides only the <command>svn</command>
      command-line client program, several third-party
      programs provide various forms of graphical client UIs.
      These GUIs use the same APIs that the stock command-line client
      does.  This type of modularity has played a large role in the
      proliferation of available Subversion clients and IDE
      integrations and, by extension, to the tremendous adoption rate
      of Subversion itself.</para>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.developer.layerlib.repos">
      <title>Repository Layer</title>

      <para>When referring to Subversion's Repository layer, we're
        generally talking about two basic concepts&mdash;the versioned
        filesystem implementation (accessed via
        <filename>libsvn_fs</filename>, and supported by its
        <filename>libsvn_fs_base</filename> and
        <filename>libsvn_fs_fs</filename> plug-ins), and the repository
        logic that wraps it (as implemented in
        <filename>libsvn_repos</filename>).  These libraries provide
        the storage and reporting mechanisms for the various revisions
        of your version-controlled data.  This layer is connected to
        the Client layer via the Repository Access layer, and is, from
        the perspective of the Subversion user, the stuff at the
        <quote>other end of the line.</quote></para>

      <para>The Subversion filesystem is not a kernel-level filesystem
        that one would install in an operating system (such as the
        Linux ext2 or NTFS), but instead is a virtual filesystem.
        Rather than storing <quote>files</quote> and
        <quote>directories</quote> as real files and directories (the
        kind you can navigate through using your favorite shell
        program), it uses one of two available abstract storage
        backends&mdash;either a Berkeley DB database environment or a
        flat-file representation.  (To learn more about the two
        repository backends, see <xref
        linkend="svn.reposadmin.basics.backends"/>.)  There has even
        been considerable interest by the development community in
        giving future releases of Subversion the ability to use other
        backend database systems, perhaps through a mechanism such as
        Open Database Connectivity (ODBC).  In fact, Google did
        something similar to this before launching the Google Code
        Project Hosting service:  they announced in mid-2006 that
        members of its open source team had written a new proprietary
        Subversion filesystem plug-in that used Google's ultra-scalable
        Bigtable database for its storage.</para>

      <para>The filesystem API exported by
        <filename>libsvn_fs</filename> contains the kinds of
        functionality you would expect from any other filesystem
        API&mdash;you can create and remove files and directories,
        copy and move them around, modify file contents, and so on.
        It also has features that are not quite as common, such as the
        ability to add, modify, and remove metadata
        (<quote>properties</quote>) on each file or directory.
        Furthermore, the Subversion filesystem is a versioning
        filesystem, which means that as you make changes to your
        directory tree, Subversion remembers what your tree looked
        like before those changes.  And before the previous changes.
        And the previous ones.  And so on, all the way back through
        versioning time to (and just beyond) the moment you first
        started adding things to the filesystem.</para>

      <para>All the modifications you make to your tree are done
        within the context of a Subversion commit transaction.  The
        following is a simplified general routine for modifying your
        filesystem:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Begin a Subversion commit transaction.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Make your changes (adds, deletes, property
            modifications, etc.).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Commit your transaction.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Once you have committed your transaction, your filesystem
        modifications are permanently stored as historical artifacts.
        Each of these cycles generates a single new revision of your
        tree, and each revision is forever accessible as an immutable
        snapshot of <quote>the way things were.</quote></para>

      <sidebar>
        <title>The Transaction Distraction</title>

        <para>The notion of a Subversion transaction can become easily
          confused with the transaction support provided by the
          underlying database itself, especially given the former's
          close proximity to the Berkeley DB database code in
          <filename>libsvn_fs_base</filename>.  Both types of
          transaction exist to provide atomicity and isolation.  In
          other words, transactions give you the ability to perform a
          set of actions in an all-or-nothing fashion&mdash;either all
          the actions in the set complete with success, or they all
          get treated as though <emphasis>none</emphasis> of them ever
          happened&mdash;and in a way that does not interfere with
          other processes acting on the data.</para>

        <para>Database transactions generally encompass small
          operations related specifically to the modification of data
          in the database itself (such as changing the contents of a
          table row).  Subversion transactions are larger in scope,
          encompassing higher-level operations such as making
          modifications to a set of files and directories that are
          intended to be stored as the next revision of the filesystem
          tree.  If that isn't confusing enough, consider the fact
          that Subversion uses a database transaction during the
          creation of a Subversion transaction (so that if the
          creation of a Subversion transaction fails, the database will
          look as though we had never attempted that creation in the first
          place)!</para>

        <para>Fortunately for users of the filesystem API, the
          transaction support provided by the database system itself
          is hidden almost entirely from view (as should be expected
          from a properly modularized library scheme).  It is only
          when you start digging into the implementation of the
          filesystem itself that such things become visible (or
          interesting).</para>

      </sidebar>

      <para>Most of the functionality the filesystem
        interface provides deals with actions that occur on individual
        filesystem paths.  That is, from outside the filesystem, the
        primary mechanism for describing and accessing the individual
        revisions of files and directories comes through the use of
        path strings such as <filename>/foo/bar</filename>, just as though
        you were addressing files and directories through your
        favorite shell program.  You add new files and directories by
        passing their paths-to-be to the right API functions.  You
        query for information about them by the same mechanism.</para>

      <para>Unlike most filesystems, though, a path alone is not
        enough information to identify a file or directory in
        Subversion.  Think of a directory tree as a two-dimensional
        system, where a node's siblings represent a sort of
        left-and-right motion, and navigating into the node's
        subdirectories represents a downward motion.  <xref
        linkend="svn.developer.layerlib.repos.dia-1"/> shows a typical
        representation of a tree as exactly that.</para>

      <figure id="svn.developer.layerlib.repos.dia-1">
        <title>Files and directories in two dimensions</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/ch08dia1.png"/>
      </figure>

      <para>The difference here is that the Subversion filesystem has a
        nifty third dimension that most filesystems do not
        have&mdash;Time!
        <footnote>
          <para>We understand that this may come as a shock to sci-fi
            fans who have long been under the impression that Time was
            actually the <emphasis>fourth</emphasis> dimension, and we
            apologize for any emotional trauma induced by our
            assertion of a different theory.</para>
        </footnote>
        In the filesystem interface, nearly every function that has a
        <parameter>path</parameter> argument also expects a
        <parameter>root</parameter> argument.  This
        <literal>svn_fs_root_t</literal> argument describes
        either a revision or a Subversion transaction (which is simply
        a revision in the making) and provides that third dimension
        of context needed to understand the difference between
        <filename>/foo/bar</filename> in revision 32, and the same
        path as it exists in revision 98.  <xref
        linkend="svn.developer.layerlib.repos.dia-2"/> shows revision
        history as an added dimension to the Subversion filesystem
        universe.</para>

      <figure id="svn.developer.layerlib.repos.dia-2">
        <title>Versioning time&mdash;the third dimension!</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/ch08dia2.png"/>
      </figure>

      <para>As we mentioned earlier, the
        <filename>libsvn_fs</filename> API looks and feels like any
        other filesystem, except that it has this wonderful versioning
        capability.  It was designed to be usable by any program
        interested in a versioning filesystem.  Not coincidentally,
        Subversion itself is interested in that functionality.  But
        while the filesystem API should be sufficient for basic file
        and directory versioning support, Subversion wants
        more&mdash;and that is where <filename>libsvn_repos</filename>
        comes in.</para>

      <para>The Subversion repository library
        (<filename>libsvn_repos</filename>) sits (logically speaking)
        atop the <filename>libsvn_fs</filename> API, providing
        additional functionality beyond that of the underlying
        versioned filesystem logic.  It does not completely wrap each
        and every filesystem function&mdash;only certain major steps
        in the general cycle of filesystem activity are wrapped by the
        repository interface.  Some of these include the creation and
        commit of Subversion transactions and the modification of
        revision properties.  These particular events are wrapped by
        the repository layer because they have hooks associated with
        them.  A repository hook system is not strictly related to
        implementing a versioning filesystem, so it lives in the
        repository wrapper library.</para>
      
      <para>The hooks mechanism is but one of the reasons for the
        abstraction of a separate repository library from the rest of
        the filesystem code.  The <filename>libsvn_repos</filename>
        API provides several other important utilities to Subversion.
        These include the abilities to:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create, open, destroy, and perform recovery steps on a
            Subversion repository and the filesystem included in that
            repository.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Describe the differences between two filesystem
            trees.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Query for the commit log messages associated with all
            (or some) of the revisions in which a set of files was
            modified in the filesystem.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Generate a human-readable <quote>dump</quote> of the
            filesystem&mdash;a complete representation of the revisions in
            the filesystem.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Parse that dump format, loading the dumped revisions
            into a different Subversion repository.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>As Subversion continues to evolve, the repository library
        will grow with the filesystem library to offer increased
        functionality and configurable option support.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.developer.layerlib.ra">
      <title>Repository Access Layer</title>

      <para>If the Subversion Repository layer is at <quote>the other
        end of the line,</quote> the Repository Access (RA) layer is
        the line itself.  Charged with marshaling data between the
        client libraries and the repository, this layer includes the
        <filename>libsvn_ra</filename> module loader library, the RA
        modules themselves (which currently includes
        <filename>libsvn_ra_neon</filename>,
        <filename>libsvn_ra_local</filename>,
        <filename>libsvn_ra_serf</filename>, and
        <filename>libsvn_ra_svn</filename>), and any additional
        libraries needed by one or more of those RA modules (such as
        the <filename>mod_dav_svn</filename> Apache module or
        <filename>libsvn_ra_svn</filename>'s server,
        <command>svnserve</command>).</para>

      <para>Since Subversion uses URLs to identify its repository
        resources, the protocol portion of the URL scheme (usually
        <literal>file://</literal>, <literal>http://</literal>,
        <literal>https://</literal>, <literal>svn://</literal>, or
        <literal>svn+ssh://</literal>) is used to determine which RA
        module will handle the communications.  Each module registers
        a list of the protocols it knows how to <quote>speak</quote>
        so that the RA loader can, at runtime, determine which module
        to use for the task at hand.  You can determine which RA
        modules are available to the Subversion command-line client,
        and what protocols they claim to support, by running
        <userinput>svn --version</userinput>:</para>
     
      <screen>
$ svn --version
svn, version 1.5.0 (r31699)
   compiled Jun 18 2008, 09:57:36

Copyright (C) 2000-2008 CollabNet.
Subversion is open source software, see http://subversion.tigris.org/
This product includes software developed by CollabNet (http://www.Collab.Net/).

The following repository access (RA) modules are available:

* ra_neon : Module for accessing a repository via WebDAV protocol using Neon.
  - handles 'http' scheme
  - handles 'https' scheme
* ra_svn : Module for accessing a repository using the svn network protocol.
  - handles 'svn' scheme
* ra_local : Module for accessing a repository on local disk.
  - handles 'file' scheme
* ra_serf : Module for accessing a repository via WebDAV protocol using serf.
  - handles 'http' scheme
  - handles 'https' scheme

$
</screen>

      <para>The public API exported by the RA layer contains
        functionality necessary for sending and receiving versioned
        data to and from the repository.  And each of the available RA
        plug-ins is able to perform that task using a specific
        protocol&mdash;<filename>libsvn_ra_dav</filename> speaks
        HTTP/WebDAV (optionally using SSL encryption) with an Apache
        HTTP Server that is running the
        <filename>mod_dav_svn</filename> Subversion server module;
        <filename>libsvn_ra_svn</filename> speaks a custom network
        protocol with the <command>svnserve</command> program; and so
        on.</para>

      <para>For those who wish to access a Subversion repository
        using still another protocol, that is precisely why the
        Repository Access layer is modularized!  Developers can simply
        write a new library that implements the RA interface on one
        side and communicates with the repository on the other.  Your
        new library can use existing network protocols or you can
        invent your own.  You could use interprocess communication
        (IPC) calls, or&mdash;let's get crazy, shall we?&mdash;you
        could even implement an email-based protocol.  Subversion
        supplies the APIs; you supply the creativity.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.developer.layerlib.client">
      <title>Client Layer</title>
      
      <para>On the client side, the Subversion working copy is where
        all the action takes place.  The bulk of functionality
        implemented by the client-side libraries exists for the sole
        purpose of managing working copies&mdash;directories full of
        files and other subdirectories that serve as a sort of local,
        editable <quote>reflection</quote> of one or more repository
        locations&mdash;and propagating changes to and from the
        Repository Access layer.</para>

      <para>Subversion's working copy library,
        <filename>libsvn_wc</filename>, is directly responsible for
        managing the data in the working copies.  To accomplish this,
        the library stores administrative information about each
        working copy directory within a special subdirectory.  This
        subdirectory, named <filename>.svn</filename>, is present in
        each working copy directory and contains various other files
        and directories that record state and provide a private
        workspace for administrative action.  For those familiar with
        CVS, this <filename>.svn</filename> subdirectory is similar in
        purpose to the <filename>CVS</filename> administrative
        directories found in CVS working copies.  For more information
        about the <filename>.svn</filename> administrative area, see
        <xref linkend="svn.developer.insidewc"/> later in this
        chapter.</para>

      <para>The Subversion client library,
        <filename>libsvn_client</filename>, has the broadest
        responsibility; its job is to mingle the functionality of the
        working copy library with that of the Repository Access layer,
        and then to provide the highest-level API to any application
        that wishes to perform general revision control actions.  For
        example, the function
        <function>svn_client_checkout()</function> takes a URL as an
        argument.  It passes this URL to the RA layer and opens an
        authenticated session with a particular repository.  It then
        asks the repository for a certain tree, and sends this tree
        into the working copy library, which then writes a full
        working copy to disk (<filename>.svn</filename> directories
        and all).</para>

      <para>The client library is designed to be used by any
        application.  While the Subversion source code includes a
        standard command-line client, it should be very easy to write
        any number of GUI clients on top of the client library.  New
        GUIs (or any new client, really) for Subversion need not be
        clunky wrappers around the included command-line
        client&mdash;they have full access via the
        <filename>libsvn_client</filename> API to the same functionality,
        data, and callback mechanisms that the command-line client
        uses.  In fact, the Subversion source code tree contains a
        small C program (which you can find at
        <filename>tools/examples/minimal_client.c</filename>) that
        exemplifies how to wield the Subversion API to create a simple
        client program.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title>Binding Directly&mdash;A Word About Correctness</title>

        <para>Why should your GUI program bind directly with a
          <filename>libsvn_client</filename> instead of acting as a
          wrapper around a command-line program?  Besides simply being
          more efficient, it can be more correct as well.  A
          command-line program (such as the one supplied with
          Subversion) that binds to the client library needs to
          effectively translate feedback and requested data bits from
          C types to some form of human-readable output.  This type of
          translation can be lossy.  That is, the program may not
          display all of the information harvested from the API or may
          combine bits of information for compact
          representation.</para>

        <para>If you wrap such a command-line program with yet another
          program, the second program has access only to
          already interpreted (and as we mentioned, likely incomplete)
          information, which it must <emphasis>again</emphasis>
          translate into <emphasis>its</emphasis> representation
          format.  With each layer of wrapping, the integrity of the
          original data is potentially tainted more and more, much
          like the result of making a copy of a copy (of a copy&hellip;)
          of a favorite audio or video cassette.</para>
 
        <para>But the most compelling argument for binding directly to
          the APIs instead of wrapping other programs is that the
          Subversion project makes compatibility promises regarding
          its APIs.  Across minor versions of those APIs (such as
          between 1.3 and 1.4), no function's prototype will change.
          In other words, you aren't forced to update your program's
          source code simply because you've upgraded to a new version
          of Subversion.  Certain functions might be deprecated, but
          they still work, and this gives you a buffer of time to
          eventually embrace the newer APIs.  These kinds of
          compatibility promises do not exist for Subversion
          command-line program output, which is subject to change from
          release to release.</para>

      </sidebar>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.developer.insidewc">
    <title>Inside the Working Copy Administration Area</title>
    
    <para>As we mentioned earlier, each directory of a Subversion
      working copy contains a special subdirectory called
      <filename>.svn</filename> that houses administrative data about
      that working copy directory.  Subversion uses the information in
      <filename>.svn</filename> to keep track of things such as:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Which repository location(s) are represented by the
          files and subdirectories in the working copy
          directory</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>What revision of each of those files and directories is
          currently present in the working copy</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Any user-defined properties that might be attached
          to those files and directories</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Pristine (unedited) copies of the working copy
          files</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The Subversion working copy administration area's layout and
      contents are considered implementation details not really
      intended for human consumption.  Developers are encouraged to
      use Subversion's public APIs, or the tools that Subversion
      provides, to access and manipulate the working copy data,
      instead of directly reading or modifying those files.  The file
      formats employed by the working copy library for its
      administrative data do change from time to time&mdash;a fact
      that the public APIs do a great job of hiding from the average
      user.  In this section, we expose some of these implementation
      details sheerly to appease your overwhelming curiosity.</para>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.developer.insidewc.entries">
      <title>The Entries File</title>

      <para>Perhaps the single most important file in the
        <filename>.svn</filename> directory is the
        <filename>entries</filename> file.  It
        contains the bulk of the administrative
        information about the versioned items in a working copy
        directory.  This one file tracks the repository
        URLs, pristine revision, file checksums, pristine text and
        property timestamps, scheduling and conflict state
        information, last-known commit information (author, revision,
        timestamp), local copy history&mdash;practically everything
        that a Subversion client is interested in knowing about a
        versioned (or to-be-versioned) resource!</para>

      <para>Folks familiar with CVS's administrative directories will
        have recognized at this point that Subversion's
        <filename>.svn/entries</filename> file serves the purposes of,
        among other things, CVS's <filename>CVS/Entries</filename>,
        <filename>CVS/Root</filename>, and
        <filename>CVS/Repository</filename> files combined.</para>

      <para>The format of the <filename>.svn/entries</filename> file
        has changed over time.  Originally an XML file, it now uses a
        custom&mdash;though still human-readable&mdash;file format.
        While XML was a great choice for early developers of
        Subversion who were frequently debugging the file's contents
        (and Subversion's behavior in light of them), the need for
        easy developer debugging has diminished as Subversion has
        matured and has been replaced by the user's need for snappier
        performance.  Be aware that Subversion's working copy library
        automatically upgrades working copies from one format to
        another&mdash;it reads the old formats and writes the
        new&mdash;which saves you the hassle of checking out a new
        working copy, but can also complicate situations where
        different versions of Subversion might be trying to use the
        same working copy.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.developer.insidewc.base-and-props">
      <title>Pristine Copies and Property Files</title>

      <para>As mentioned before, the <filename>.svn</filename>
        directory also holds the pristine <quote>text-base</quote>
        versions of files.  You can find those in
        <filename>.svn/text-base</filename>.  The benefits of these
        pristine copies are multiple&mdash;network-free checks for
        local modifications and difference reporting, network-free
        reversion of modified or missing files, more efficient
        transmission of changes to the server&mdash;but they come at the
        cost of having each versioned file stored at least twice on
        disk.  These days, this seems to be a negligible penalty for
        most files.  However, the situation gets uglier as the size of
        your versioned files grows.  Some attention is being given to
        making the presence of the <quote>text-base</quote> an option.
        Ironically, though, it is as your versioned files' sizes get
        larger that the existence of the <quote>text-base</quote>
        becomes more crucial&mdash;who wants to transmit a huge file
        across a network just because she wants to commit a tiny
        change to it?</para>

      <para>Similar in purpose to the <quote>text-base</quote> files
        are the property files and their pristine
        <quote>prop-base</quote> copies, located in
        <filename>.svn/props</filename> and
        <filename>.svn/prop-base</filename>, respectively.  Since
        directories can have properties too, there are also
        <filename>.svn/dir-props</filename> and
        <filename>.svn/dir-prop-base</filename> files.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.developer.usingapi">
    <title>Using the APIs</title>

    <para>Developing applications against the Subversion library APIs
      is fairly straightforward.  Subversion is primarily a set of C
      libraries, with header (<filename>.h</filename>) files that live
      in the <filename>subversion/include</filename> directory of the
      source tree.  These headers are copied into your system
      locations (e.g., <filename>/usr/local/include</filename>)
      when you build and install Subversion itself from source.  These
      headers represent the entirety of the functions and types meant
      to be accessible by users of the Subversion libraries.  The
      Subversion developer community is meticulous about ensuring that
      the public API is well documented&mdash;refer directly to the
      header files for that documentation.</para>

    <para>When examining the public header files, the first thing you
      might notice is that Subversion's datatypes and functions are
      namespace-protected.  That is, every public Subversion symbol
      name begins with <literal>svn_</literal>, followed by a short
      code for the library in which the symbol is defined (such as
      <literal>wc</literal>, <literal>client</literal>,
      <literal>fs</literal>, etc.), followed by a single underscore
      (<literal>_</literal>), and then the rest of the symbol name.
      Semipublic functions (used among source files of a given
      library but not by code outside that library, and found inside
      the library directories themselves) differ from this naming
      scheme in that instead of a single underscore after the library
      code, they use a double underscore
      (<literal>_&thinsp;_</literal>).  Functions that are private to
      a given source file have no special prefixing and are declared
      <literal>static</literal>.  Of course, a compiler isn't
      interested in these naming conventions, but they help to clarify
      the scope of a given function or datatype.</para>

    <para>Another good source of information about programming against
      the Subversion APIs is the project's own hacking guidelines,
      which you can find at <ulink
      url="http://subversion.tigris.org/hacking.html" />.  This
      document contains useful information, which, while aimed at
      developers and would-be developers of Subversion itself, is
      equally applicable to folks developing against Subversion as a
      set of third-party libraries.
      <footnote>
        <para>After all, Subversion uses Subversion's APIs,
          too.</para>
      </footnote>
    </para>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.developer.usingapi.apr">
      <title>The Apache Portable Runtime Library</title>

      <para>Along with Subversion's own datatypes, you will see many
        references to datatypes that begin with
        <literal>apr_</literal>&mdash;symbols from the Apache Portable
        Runtime (APR) library.  APR is Apache's portability library,
        originally carved out of its server code as an attempt to
        separate the OS-specific bits from the OS-independent portions
        of the code.  The result was a library that provides a generic
        API for performing operations that differ mildly&mdash;or
        wildly&mdash;from OS to OS.  While the Apache HTTP Server was
        obviously the first user of the APR library, the Subversion
        developers immediately recognized the value of using APR as
        well.  This means that there is practically no OS-specific
        code in Subversion itself.  Also, it means that the Subversion
        client compiles and runs anywhere that the Apache HTTP Server
        does.  Currently, this list includes all flavors of Unix,
        Win32, BeOS, OS/2, and Mac OS X.</para>

      <para>In addition to providing consistent implementations of
        system calls that differ across operating systems,
        <footnote>
          <para>Subversion uses ANSI system calls and datatypes as much
            as possible.</para>
        </footnote>
        APR gives Subversion immediate access to many custom
        datatypes, such as dynamic arrays and hash tables.  Subversion
        uses these types extensively.  But
        perhaps the most pervasive APR datatype, found in nearly every
        Subversion API prototype, is the
        <literal>apr_pool_t</literal>&mdash;the APR memory pool.
        Subversion uses pools internally for all its memory allocation
        needs (unless an external library requires a different memory
        management mechanism for data passed through its API),
        <footnote>
          <para>Neon and Berkeley DB are examples of such libraries.</para>
        </footnote>
        and while a person coding against the Subversion APIs is not
        required to do the same, she <emphasis>is</emphasis>
        required to provide pools to the API functions that need them.
        This means that users of the Subversion API must also link
        against APR, must call <function>apr_initialize()</function>
        to initialize the APR subsystem, and then must create and
        manage pools for use with Subversion API calls, typically by
        using <function>svn_pool_create()</function>,
        <function>svn_pool_clear()</function>, and
        <function>svn_pool_destroy()</function>.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title>Programming with Memory Pools</title>

        <para>Almost every developer who has used the C programming
          language has at some point sighed at the daunting task of
          managing memory usage.  Allocating enough memory to use,
          keeping track of those allocations, freeing the memory when
          you no longer need it&mdash;these tasks can be quite
          complex.  And of course, failure to do those things properly
          can result in a program that crashes itself, or worse,
          crashes the computer.</para>

        <para>Higher-level languages, on the other hand, either take
          the job of memory management away from you completely or
          make it something you toy with only when doing extremely
          tight program optimization.  Languages such as Java and
          Python use <firstterm>garbage collection</firstterm>,
          allocating memory for objects when needed, and automatically
          freeing that memory when the object is no longer in
          use.</para>

        <para>APR provides a middle-ground approach called
          <firstterm>pool-based memory management</firstterm>.  It
          allows the developer to control memory usage at a lower
          resolution&mdash;per chunk (or <quote>pool</quote>) of
          memory, instead of per allocated object.  Rather than using
          <function>malloc()</function> and friends to allocate enough
          memory for a given object, you ask APR to allocate the
          memory from a memory pool.  When you're finished using the
          objects you've created in the pool, you destroy the entire
          pool, effectively de-allocating the memory consumed by
          <emphasis>all</emphasis> the objects you allocated from it.
          Thus, rather than keeping track of individual objects that
          need to be de-allocated, your program simply considers the
          general lifetimes of those objects and allocates the objects
          in a pool whose lifetime (the time between the pool's
          creation and its deletion) matches the object's
          needs.</para>

      </sidebar>
    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.developer.usingapi.urlpath">
      <title>URL and Path Requirements</title>

      <para>With remote version control operation as the whole point
        of Subversion's existence, it makes sense that some attention
        has been paid to internationalization (i18n) support.  After
        all, while <quote>remote</quote> might mean <quote>across the
        office,</quote> it could just as well mean <quote>across the
        globe.</quote> To facilitate this, all of Subversion's public
        interfaces that accept path arguments expect those paths to be
        canonicalized&mdash;which is most easily accomplished by passing
        them through the <function>svn_path_canonicalize()</function>
        function&mdash;and encoded in UTF-8.  This means, for example, that
        any new client binary that drives the
        <filename>libsvn_client</filename> interface needs to first
        convert paths from the locale-specific encoding to UTF-8
        before passing those paths to the Subversion libraries, and
        then reconvert any resultant output paths from Subversion
        back into the locale's encoding before using those paths for
        non-Subversion purposes.  Fortunately, Subversion provides a
        suite of functions (see
        <filename>subversion/include/svn_utf.h</filename>) that 
        any program can use to do these conversions.</para>

      <para>Also, Subversion APIs require all URL parameters to be
        properly URI-encoded.  So, instead of passing
        <uri>file:///home/username/My File.txt</uri> as the URL of a
        file named <filename>My File.txt</filename>, you need to pass
        <uri>file:///home/username/My%20File.txt</uri>.  Again,
        Subversion supplies helper functions that your application can
        use&mdash;<function>svn_path_uri_encode()</function> and
        <function>svn_path_uri_decode()</function>, for URI encoding
        and decoding, respectively.</para> </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.developer.usingapi.otherlangs">
      <title>Using Languages Other Than C and C++</title> 

      <para>If you are interested in using the Subversion libraries in
        conjunction with something other than a C program&mdash;say, a
        Python or Perl script&mdash;Subversion has some support for this
        via the Simplified Wrapper and Interface Generator (SWIG).  The
        SWIG bindings for Subversion are located in
        <filename>subversion/bindings/swig</filename>.  They are still
        maturing, but they are usable.  These bindings allow you
        to call Subversion API functions indirectly, using wrappers that
        translate the datatypes native to your scripting language into
        the datatypes needed by Subversion's C libraries.</para>

      <para>Significant efforts have been made toward creating
        functional SWIG-generated bindings for Python, Perl, and Ruby.
        To some extent, the work done preparing the SWIG interface
        files for these languages is reusable in efforts to generate
        bindings for other languages supported by SWIG (which include
        versions of C#, Guile, Java, MzScheme, OCaml, PHP, and Tcl,
        among others).  However, some extra programming is required to
        compensate for complex APIs that SWIG needs some help
        translating between languages.  For more information on SWIG
        itself, see the project's web site at <ulink
        url="http://www.swig.org/"/>.</para>

      <para>Subversion also has language bindings for Java.  The
        javahl bindings (located in
        <filename>subversion/bindings/java</filename> in the
        Subversion source tree) aren't SWIG-based, but are instead a
        mixture of Java and hand-coded JNI.  Javahl covers most
        Subversion client-side APIs and is specifically targeted at
        implementors of Java-based Subversion clients and IDE
        integrations.</para>

      <para>Subversion's language bindings tend to lack the level of
        developer attention given to the core Subversion modules, but
        can generally be trusted as production-ready.  A number of
        scripts and applications, alternative Subversion GUI clients,
        and other third-party tools are successfully using
        Subversion's language bindings today to accomplish their
        Subversion integrations.</para>

      <para>It's worth noting here that there are other options for
        interfacing with Subversion using other languages:  alternative
        bindings for Subversion that aren't provided by the
        Subversion development community at all.  You can find links
        to these alternative bindings on the Subversion project's
        links page (at <ulink
        url="http://subversion.tigris.org/links.html" />), but there
        are a couple of popular ones we feel are especially
        noteworthy.  First, Barry Scott's PySVN bindings (<ulink
        url="http://pysvn.tigris.org/" />) are a popular option for
        binding with Python.  PySVN boasts of a more Pythonic
        interface than the more C-like APIs provided by Subversion's
        own Python bindings.  And if you're looking for a pure Java
        implementation of Subversion, check out SVNKit (<ulink
        url="http://svnkit.com/" />), which is Subversion rewritten
        from the ground up in Java.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title>SVNKit Versus javahl</title>

        <para>In 2005, a small company called TMate announced the
          1.0.0 release of JavaSVN&mdash;a pure Java implementation of
          Subversion.  Since then, the project has been renamed to
          SVNKit (available at <ulink url="http://svnkit.com/" />)
          and has seen great success as a provider of Subversion
          functionality to various Subversion clients, IDE
          integrations, and other third-party tools.</para>

        <para>The SVNKit library is interesting in that, unlike the
          javahl library, it is not merely a wrapper around the
          official Subversion core libraries.  In fact, it shares no
          code with Subversion at all.  But while it is easy to
          confuse SVNKit with javahl, and easier still to not even
          realize which of these libraries you are using, folks should
          be aware that SVNKit differs from javahl in some significant
          ways.  First, SVNKit is not developed as open source
          software and seems to have at any given time only a few
          developers working on it.  Also, SVNKit's license is more
          restrictive than that of Subversion.  Finally, by aiming to
          be a pure Java Subversion library, SVNKit is limited in
          which portions of Subversion can be reasonably cloned while
          still keeping up with Subversion's releases.  This has
          already happened once&mdash;SVNKit cannot access BDB-backed
          Subversion repositories via the <literal>file://</literal>
          protocol because there's no pure Java implementation of
          Berkeley DB that is file-format-compatible with the native
          implementation of that library.</para>

        <para>That said, SVNKit has a well-established track record of
          reliability.  And a pure Java solution is much more robust
          in the face of programming errors&mdash;a bug in SVNKit
          might raise a catchable Java Exception, but a bug in the Subversion core
          libraries as accessed via javahl can bring down your entire
          Java Runtime Environment.  So, weigh the costs when choosing
          a Java-based Subversion implementation.</para>

      </sidebar>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.developer.usingapi.codesamples">
      <title>Code Samples</title> 

      <para><xref linkend="svn.developer.layerlib.repos.ex-1" />
        contains a code segment (written in C) that illustrates some
        of the concepts we've been discussing.  It uses both the
        repository and filesystem interfaces (as can be determined by
        the prefixes <literal>svn_repos_</literal> and
        <literal>svn_fs_</literal> of the function names,
        respectively) to create a new revision in which a directory is
        added.  You can see the use of an APR pool, which is passed
        around for memory allocation purposes.  Also, the code reveals
        a somewhat obscure fact about Subversion error
        handling&mdash;all Subversion errors must be explicitly
        handled to avoid memory leakage (and in some cases,
        application failure).</para>

      <example id="svn.developer.layerlib.repos.ex-1">
        <title>Using the Repository Layer</title>

        <programlisting>
/* Convert a Subversion error into a simple boolean error code.
 *
 * NOTE:  Subversion errors must be cleared (using svn_error_clear())
 *        because they are allocated from the global pool, else memory
 *        leaking occurs.
 */
#define INT_ERR(expr)                           \
  do {                                          \
    svn_error_t *__temperr = (expr);            \
    if (__temperr)                              \
      {                                         \
        svn_error_clear(__temperr);             \
        return 1;                               \
      }                                         \
    return 0;                                   \
  } while (0)

/* Create a new directory at the path NEW_DIRECTORY in the Subversion
 * repository located at REPOS_PATH.  Perform all memory allocation in
 * POOL.  This function will create a new revision for the addition of
 * NEW_DIRECTORY.  Return zero if the operation completes
 * successfully, nonzero otherwise.
 */
static int
make_new_directory(const char *repos_path,
                   const char *new_directory,
                   apr_pool_t *pool)
{
  svn_error_t *err;
  svn_repos_t *repos;
  svn_fs_t *fs;
  svn_revnum_t youngest_rev;
  svn_fs_txn_t *txn;
  svn_fs_root_t *txn_root;
  const char *conflict_str;

  /* Open the repository located at REPOS_PATH. 
   */
  INT_ERR(svn_repos_open(&amp;repos, repos_path, pool));

  /* Get a pointer to the filesystem object that is stored in REPOS. 
   */
  fs = svn_repos_fs(repos);

  /* Ask the filesystem to tell us the youngest revision that
   * currently exists. 
   */
  INT_ERR(svn_fs_youngest_rev(&amp;youngest_rev, fs, pool));

  /* Begin a new transaction that is based on YOUNGEST_REV.  We are
   * less likely to have our later commit rejected as conflicting if we
   * always try to make our changes against a copy of the latest snapshot
   * of the filesystem tree. 
   */
  INT_ERR(svn_repos_fs_begin_txn_for_commit2(&amp;txn, repos, youngest_rev,
                                             apr_hash_make(pool), pool));

  /* Now that we have started a new Subversion transaction, get a root
   * object that represents that transaction. 
   */
  INT_ERR(svn_fs_txn_root(&amp;txn_root, txn, pool));
  
  /* Create our new directory under the transaction root, at the path
   * NEW_DIRECTORY. 
   */
  INT_ERR(svn_fs_make_dir(txn_root, new_directory, pool));

  /* Commit the transaction, creating a new revision of the filesystem
   * which includes our added directory path.
   */
  err = svn_repos_fs_commit_txn(&amp;conflict_str, repos, 
                                &amp;youngest_rev, txn, pool);
  if (! err)
    {
      /* No error?  Excellent!  Print a brief report of our success.
       */
      printf("Directory '%s' was successfully added as new revision "
             "'%ld'.\n", new_directory, youngest_rev);
    }
  else if (err-&gt;apr_err == SVN_ERR_FS_CONFLICT)
    {
      /* Uh-oh.  Our commit failed as the result of a conflict
       * (someone else seems to have made changes to the same area 
       * of the filesystem that we tried to modify).  Print an error
       * message.
       */
      printf("A conflict occurred at path '%s' while attempting "
             "to add directory '%s' to the repository at '%s'.\n", 
             conflict_str, new_directory, repos_path);
    }
  else
    {
      /* Some other error has occurred.  Print an error message.
       */
      printf("An error occurred while attempting to add directory '%s' "
             "to the repository at '%s'.\n", 
             new_directory, repos_path);
    }

  INT_ERR(err);
} 
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>Note that in <xref
        linkend="svn.developer.layerlib.repos.ex-1" />, the code could
        just as easily have committed the transaction using
        <function>svn_fs_commit_txn()</function>.  But the filesystem
        API knows nothing about the repository library's hook
        mechanism.  If you want your Subversion repository to
        automatically perform some set of non-Subversion tasks every
        time you commit a transaction (e.g., sending an
        email that describes all the changes made in that transaction
        to your developer mailing list), you need to use the
        <filename>libsvn_repos</filename>-wrapped version of that
        function, which adds the hook triggering
        functionality&mdash;in this case,
        <function>svn_repos_fs_commit_txn()</function>.  (For more
        information regarding Subversion's repository hooks, see <xref
        linkend="svn.reposadmin.create.hooks" />.)</para>

      <para>Now let's switch languages.  <xref
        linkend="svn.developer.usingapi.otherlangs.ex-1" /> is a
        sample program that uses Subversion's SWIG Python bindings to
        recursively crawl the youngest repository revision, and to
        print the various paths reached during the crawl.</para>

      <example id="svn.developer.usingapi.otherlangs.ex-1">
        <title>Using the Repository layer with Python</title>

        <programlisting>
#!/usr/bin/python

"""Crawl a repository, printing versioned object path names."""

import sys
import os.path
import svn.fs, svn.core, svn.repos

def crawl_filesystem_dir(root, directory):
    """Recursively crawl DIRECTORY under ROOT in the filesystem, and return
    a list of all the paths at or below DIRECTORY."""

    # Print the name of this path.
    print directory + "/"
    
    # Get the directory entries for DIRECTORY.
    entries = svn.fs.svn_fs_dir_entries(root, directory)

    # Loop over the entries.
    names = entries.keys()
    for name in names:
        # Calculate the entry's full path.
        full_path = directory + '/' + name

        # If the entry is a directory, recurse.  The recursion will return
        # a list with the entry and all its children, which we will add to
        # our running list of paths.
        if svn.fs.svn_fs_is_dir(root, full_path):
            crawl_filesystem_dir(root, full_path)
        else:
            # Else it's a file, so print its path here.
            print full_path

def crawl_youngest(repos_path):
    """Open the repository at REPOS_PATH, and recursively crawl its
    youngest revision."""
    
    # Open the repository at REPOS_PATH, and get a reference to its
    # versioning filesystem.
    repos_obj = svn.repos.svn_repos_open(repos_path)
    fs_obj = svn.repos.svn_repos_fs(repos_obj)

    # Query the current youngest revision.
    youngest_rev = svn.fs.svn_fs_youngest_rev(fs_obj)
    
    # Open a root object representing the youngest (HEAD) revision.
    root_obj = svn.fs.svn_fs_revision_root(fs_obj, youngest_rev)

    # Do the recursive crawl.
    crawl_filesystem_dir(root_obj, "")
    
if __name__ == "__main__":
    # Check for sane usage.
    if len(sys.argv) != 2:
        sys.stderr.write("Usage: %s REPOS_PATH\n"
                         % (os.path.basename(sys.argv[0])))
        sys.exit(1)

    # Canonicalize the repository path.
    repos_path = svn.core.svn_path_canonicalize(sys.argv[1])

    # Do the real work.
    crawl_youngest(repos_path)
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>This same program in C would need to deal with APR's
        memory pool system.  But Python handles memory usage
        automatically, and Subversion's Python bindings adhere to that
        convention.  In C, you'd be working with custom datatypes
        (such as those provided by the APR library) for representing
        the hash of entries and the list of paths, but Python has
        hashes (called <quote>dictionaries</quote>) and lists as
        built-in datatypes, and it provides a rich collection of
        functions for operating on those types.  So SWIG (with the
        help of some customizations in Subversion's language bindings
        layer) takes care of mapping those custom datatypes into the
        native datatypes of the target language.  This provides a more
        intuitive interface for users of that language.</para>

      <para>The Subversion Python bindings can be used for working
        copy operations, too.  In the previous section of this
        chapter, we mentioned the <filename>libsvn_client</filename>
        interface and how it exists for the sole purpose of
        simplifying the process of writing a Subversion client.  <xref
        linkend="svn.developer.usingapi.otherlangs.ex-2" /> is a brief
        example of how that library can be accessed via the SWIG
        Python bindings to re-create a scaled-down version of the
        <command>svn status</command> command.</para>

      <example id="svn.developer.usingapi.otherlangs.ex-2">
        <title>A Python status crawler</title>

        <programlisting>
#!/usr/bin/env python

"""Crawl a working copy directory, printing status information."""

import sys
import os.path
import getopt
import svn.core, svn.client, svn.wc

def generate_status_code(status):
    """Translate a status value into a single-character status code,
    using the same logic as the Subversion command-line client."""
    code_map = { svn.wc.svn_wc_status_none        : ' ',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_normal      : ' ',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_added       : 'A',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_missing     : '!',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_incomplete  : '!',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_deleted     : 'D',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_replaced    : 'R',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_modified    : 'M',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_merged      : 'G',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_conflicted  : 'C',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_obstructed  : '~',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_ignored     : 'I',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_external    : 'X',
                 svn.wc.svn_wc_status_unversioned : '?',
               }
    return code_map.get(status, '?')

def do_status(wc_path, verbose):
    # Build a client context baton.
    ctx = svn.client.svn_client_ctx_t()

    def _status_callback(path, status):
        """A callback function for svn_client_status."""

        # Print the path, minus the bit that overlaps with the root of
        # the status crawl
        text_status = generate_status_code(status.text_status)
        prop_status = generate_status_code(status.prop_status)
        print '%s%s  %s' % (text_status, prop_status, path)
        
    # Do the status crawl, using _status_callback() as our callback function.
    revision = svn.core.svn_opt_revision_t()
    revision.type = svn.core.svn_opt_revision_head
    svn.client.svn_client_status2(wc_path, revision, _status_callback,
                                  svn.core.svn_depth_infinity, verbose,
                                  0, 0, 1, ctx)

def usage_and_exit(errorcode):
    """Print usage message, and exit with ERRORCODE."""
    stream = errorcode and sys.stderr or sys.stdout
    stream.write("""Usage: %s OPTIONS WC-PATH
Options:
  --help, -h    : Show this usage message
  --verbose, -v : Show all statuses, even uninteresting ones
""" % (os.path.basename(sys.argv[0])))
    sys.exit(errorcode)
    
if __name__ == '__main__':
    # Parse command-line options.
    try:
        opts, args = getopt.getopt(sys.argv[1:], "hv", ["help", "verbose"])
    except getopt.GetoptError:
        usage_and_exit(1)
    verbose = 0
    for opt, arg in opts:
        if opt in ("-h", "--help"):
            usage_and_exit(0)
        if opt in ("-v", "--verbose"):
            verbose = 1
    if len(args) != 1:
        usage_and_exit(2)
            
    # Canonicalize the repository path.
    wc_path = svn.core.svn_path_canonicalize(args[0])

    # Do the real work.
    try:
        do_status(wc_path, verbose)
    except svn.core.SubversionException, e:
        sys.stderr.write("Error (%d): %s\n" % (e.apr_err, e.message))
        sys.exit(1)
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>As was the case in <xref
        linkend="svn.developer.usingapi.otherlangs.ex-1" />, this
        program is pool-free and uses, for the most part, normal
        Python datatypes.  The call to
        <function>svn_client_ctx_t()</function> is deceiving because
        the public Subversion API has no such function&mdash;this just
        happens to be a case where SWIG's automatic language
        generation bleeds through a little bit (the function is a sort
        of factory function for Python's version of the corresponding
        complex C structure).  Also note that the path passed to this
        program (like the last one) gets run through
        <function>svn_path_canonicalize()</function>, because to
        <emphasis>not</emphasis> do so runs the risk of triggering the
        underlying Subversion C library's assertions about such
        things, which translates into rather immediate and
        unceremonious program abortion.</para>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.developer.summary">
    <title>Summary</title>

    <para>One of Subversion's greatest features isn't something you
      get from running its command-line client or other tools.  It's
      the fact that Subversion was designed modularly and provides a
      stable, public API so that others&mdash;like yourself,
      perhaps&mdash;can write custom software that drives Subversion's
      core logic.</para>

    <para>In this chapter, we took a closer look at Subversion's
      architecture, examining its logical layers and describing that
      public API, the very same API that Subversion's own layers use
      to communicate with each other.  Many developers have found
      interesting uses for the Subversion API, from simple repository
      hook scripts, to integrations between Subversion and some other
      application, to completely different version control systems.
      What unique itch will <emphasis>you</emphasis> scratch with
      it?</para>

  </sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
